<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/2.3/journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="2.3" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="e-issn">23519924</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Migration History</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JMH</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">2351-9916</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2351-9924</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Brill</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Leiden</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1163/23519924-00201001</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Practices of Displacement: Forced Migration of Mixed-Race Children from Colonial Ruanda-Urundi to Belgium</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Heynssens</surname><given-names>Sarah</given-names></name>
<aff><institution>University of Antwerp</institution>, <email>Sarah.heynssens@gmail.com</email></aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>03</month><year>2016</year></pub-date>
<volume>2</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>31</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>&#x00A9; 2016 by Koninklijke Brill NV, Leiden, The Netherlands</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Koninklijke Brill NV incorporates the imprints Brill, Brill Hes &amp; De Graaf, Brill Nijhoff, Brill Rodopi and Hotei Publishing.</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="23519924_002_01_S001_text.pdf"/>
<abstract>
<p>During colonial times, the Belgian metropolitan government removed mixed-race children from their indigenous African families and placed them in specialised institutions. On the eve of independence about 300 of these children were &#x2018;evacuated&#x2019; to Belgium. This article elaborates on Belgian policy towards mixed-race children during the colonial era and on the forced displacement of mixed-race children from the Ruanda-Urundi region upon independence. It reflects on the ways in which indigenous parents reacted to and protested against the displacement of their children and investigates how the colonial government tried to neutralise objections. The article confronts the factual practices of displacement with the perceptions of the various actors involved, which allows discerning notions about race, citizenship, motherhood and child rearing.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>colonialism</kwd>
<kwd>segregation</kwd>
<kwd>migration</kwd>
<kwd>childhood</kwd>
<kwd>indigenous protest</kwd>
<kwd>Ruanda-Urundi</kwd>
<kwd>mixed-race</kwd>
<kwd>Belgium</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>2.3</meta-name><meta-value>fulltext</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>&#x002A; An earlier version of this article was presented at the 16th Berkshire Conference on the History of Women, Toronto, Canada, 23 May 2014 during the workshop &#x2018;Colonialism and Indigenous Mothers: Comparative Studies in Child Removals in the 16th-20th Centuries&#x2019;. I thank Henk de Smaele, Mathieu Roeges, Sander Veraverbeke and Leah Kazar for their comments and corrections. The financing of the archival work and research necessary for the redaction of this paper has been provided by the Centre for Historical Research and Documentation on War and Contemporary Society and Antwerp University.</p>
<sec sec-type="head1" id="B10.1163_23519924_00201001_001"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Belgian society has been blamed of being indifferent and unwilling to take responsibility for the wrongdoings of its colonial past. In 2001, Ludo De Witte&#x2019;s reassessment of the assassination of Lumumba and Adam Hochschild&#x2019;s reflection on the exploitation of the Congo Free State initiated the belated acknowledgement of certain key events.<xref rid="fn2" ref-type="fn"><sup>1</sup></xref> The displacement of Eurafrican children is an episode that elicited public attention. During colonial times, the Belgian metropolitan government removed thousands of mixed-race children from their indigenous families. On the eve of independence, in the early 1960s, several hundreds of these children from the Ruanda-Urundi region were &#x2018;evacuated&#x2019; to Belgium. Many African parents and families consider this &#x2018;evacuation&#x2019; to be a blunt kidnap. This displacement has incited public debate in Belgium. In 2010 scholar Luc Huyse made a plea to convene a parliamentary &#x2018;truth commission&#x2019;<xref rid="fn3" ref-type="fn"><sup>2</sup></xref> and in 2015 the Flemish parliament established a research commission to look into the matter and issued a public apology for the forced displacements.<xref rid="fn4" ref-type="fn"><sup>3</sup></xref></p>
<p>Recently, scholars have made attempts to improve our understanding of the national and cultural politics behind several colonial child displacements. They demonstrated that politics of child displacement are strong indicators of ideas of nation, race and class and that these concepts were important incentives for dislocation. Mixed race people stood on the edge of colonial categories and therefore challenged the colonial logic that separated &#x2018;black&#x2019; from &#x2018;white&#x2019; and coloniser from colonised. Children were seen as an especially vulnerable demographic as they were still malleable and mirrored adult society. Child welfare was increasingly linked to national interest, as youth embodied the nation&#x2019;s future. Colonial authorities feared that without European intervention this group would degenerate and reflect poorly on European identity and authority. Mixed race boys would become paupers, vagabonds or revolutionaries wanting to overthrow the colonial state; girls risked sliding into prostitution.<xref rid="fn5" ref-type="fn"><sup>4</sup></xref></p>
<p>As such mixed race children were problematised as both &#x2018;at risk and a risk&#x2019; within colonial society.<xref rid="fn6" ref-type="fn"><sup>5</sup></xref> Sometimes the neutralisation for this threat was sought through the removal of children from dangerous indigenous influences and the correction of their racial predispositions through cultural education. Indeed, during the colonial era French<xref rid="fn7" ref-type="fn"><sup>6</sup></xref> and English<xref rid="fn8" ref-type="fn"><sup>7</sup></xref> authorities removed thousands of children of mixed descent (<italic>m&#x00E9;tis</italic>) from their mothers and kin and placed them in state-run institutions where they received a tailored education. The Belgian case is conspicuously absent from this historiography. However Belgian colonial powers systematically removed mixed race children from their African families as well.</p>
<p>Just before independence, from 1959 to 1961, 283 of these displaced children from the former trust territory Ruanda-Urundi were &#x2018;repatriated&#x2019; to Belgium. In 1916, Belgian forces had conquered the ancient kingdoms of Rwanda and Burundi on the Germans. In 1924 the area became officially unified as the League of Nations mandate area &#x2018;Ruanda-Urundi&#x2019; under Belgian supervision. In 1945 it became a United Nations Trust region, still under Belgian supervision. The region became independent in 1962 at which point it separated along traditional lines in Rwanda and Burundi. The &#x2018;repatriation&#x2019; of children from the former trust area was unusual because Eurafrican children living in institutions in the Belgian Congo were not moved to Belgium. Furthermore, non-recognised <italic>m&#x00E9;tis</italic> had no means of obtaining Belgian nationality or citizenship. As a consequence, their displacement to the metropolis after independence was less evident than in France, for example, where thousands of Eurasian children were repatriated after the independence of French Indochina.<xref rid="fn9" ref-type="fn"><sup>8</sup></xref> Their displacement does show some parallels with the &#x2018;evacuation&#x2019; of non-Dutch Eurasians to the Netherlands during the late 1950s and 1960s.<xref rid="fn10" ref-type="fn"><sup>9</sup></xref> The British and Dutch, however, did not move children in large numbers to Europe.</p>
<p>This article seeks to explain why the decision to displace the Eurafrican children to Belgium was taken and why it remains an extremely controversial decision today. Indeed, the displacement of these children is swathed in controversy and gave rise to simplistic opposing narratives of &#x2018;rescue&#x2019; and &#x2018;kidnap&#x2019;. At the time of the transfer, the Belgian authorities and press recounted the story of &#x2018;abandoned children in need of rescue&#x2019;.<xref rid="fn11" ref-type="fn"><sup>10</sup></xref> In recent years, however, displaced children, documentary makers and the media have formulated a more complex narrative that voices the experiences of the children themselves and of their indigenous mothers, who often refute having abandoned their children.<xref rid="fn12" ref-type="fn"><sup>11</sup></xref> This ambiguity calls for a reassessment of the position of mixed race children within colonial society. What legal and social position did they have in colonial society? Why were they removed from their indigenous families and brought to Belgium upon independence? What caused this double dislocation?</p>
<p>To understand why diverging accounts exist of this particular instance of child displacement, it is necessary examine the cultural and legislative &#x2018;contagion&#x2019; the encounter of two widely diverse cultures caused in an ever-changing colonial society. Therefore, this article first analyses the context in which mixed-race children were born: who were their parents and what was the nature of the relationship between these parents? Secondly, the motives and practices of the subsequent displacements of the children will be discussed. I will show why and how several thousands of biracial children from both the Belgian Congo and Ruanda-Urundi were placed in institutions with an adapted educational system during colonial times. Section three, will explore the subsequent displacement of some 300 of these children from the Ruanda-Urundi region to Belgium on the eve of independence. Both displacements were embedded in a legislative framework concerning morally abandoned children. I will show that although the displacement was often portrayed as humanitarian, other motives were active and played an important role in the decision process. Lastly, in section four, I will investigate how indigenous parents resisted the displacement of their children and what counter-tactics colonial authorities applied in response to these strategies.</p>
<p>In exploring these issues, particular attention shall be paid to the subaltern groups involved in this specific historic episode. Mixed-race children and their indigenous mothers have remained obscure in the liminal zones of colonial historiography. Knowledge about interracial relationships and African women during colonial times is hard to acquire. Women involved in such interracial relationships have remained somewhat phantom-like entities, as written sources revealing their identity, motives and sentiments are scarce and rarely allow for in-depth analysis. The case of the displaced children from Ruanda-Urundi and the diversity of sources concerning this case offer a unique perspective on this complex issue.</p>
<p>In Belgian colonial territories, authorities ordered the registration of all biracial children and from 1948 onwards, they installed a <italic>recherche de paternit&#x00E9;</italic> (paternity investigations) in order to determine the biological fathers of the children.<xref rid="fn13" ref-type="fn"><sup>12</sup></xref> During this <italic>recherche de paternit&#x00E9;</italic>, presumed fathers, mothers and witnesses of interracial relationships were interviewed about the nature and duration of their relationships and the care of the children. Even though the authorities seldom succeeded in verifying the paternity, the <italic>recherche de paternit&#x00E9;</italic> does offer a rich source of information on the interactions between European men and African women.<xref rid="fn14" ref-type="fn"><sup>13</sup></xref> Additionally, reports by both the authorities and non-governmental organisations involved in the transfer of the children provide insights in the modalities and motives of the displacements.<xref rid="fn15" ref-type="fn"><sup>14</sup></xref></p>
<p>The sources mentioned above often prove to be less informative when it comes to illuminating the experiences, strategies and actions of the subjects of colonial policy. In this respect ego-documents provide solace. Several mothers wrote letters to the organisations responsible for transferring their children to Belgium. In these letters, they denounced the displacements and asked for the whereabouts of their children. Likewise, interviews with children, adoptive families, indigenous mothers, missionaries and organisational officials offer a rare glimpse into the inner lives, motives and aspirations of the different parties involved.<xref rid="fn16" ref-type="fn"><sup>15</sup></xref></p>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_23519924_00201001_002" sec-type="head1"><title>Interracial Relationships and Mixed-Race Children</title>
<p>In the early years of the Belgian presence in the Congo interracial sexual contact was tolerated and even welcomed. It was believed that the so-called <italic>m&#x00E9;nag&#x00E8;res</italic> and concubines could result in a better understanding and control of the indigenous populations. By the time the Belgian colonial realm was expanded into the territory of the pre-colonial kingdoms of Rwanda and Burundi in 1919, authorities tried to regulate and restrict interracial relationships.<xref rid="fn17" ref-type="fn"><sup>16</sup></xref> By then the Victorian standards of morality had found their way into the colonial undertaking. Colonial authorities engaged in the &#x2018;<italic>mission civilisatrice</italic>&#x2019; and concubinage did not align with their new values. As a result, colonial powers feared that interracial unions would undermine the authority of the established colonial power and would lead to a degeneration of the European population in the colony.<xref rid="fn18" ref-type="fn"><sup>17</sup></xref> The efforts taken by the colonial government, however, could not prevent interracial relations to live on.</p>
<p>The most prevalent relationships were between European men and African women. The opposite combination was very rare, but occurred as well. Some European women slept with Congolese, Rwandese or Burundian men. Even more than encounters between European men and African women, these relationships were perceived as scandalous and therefore commonly covered in a veil of secrecy.<xref rid="fn19" ref-type="fn"><sup>18</sup></xref> In the region of Ruanda-Urundi authorities recorded only 5 of this pattern on a total of 881 interracial relationships.<xref rid="fn20" ref-type="fn"><sup>19</sup></xref> Encounters between European men and African women, although hardly respected and mostly disapproved of by many Europeans, were displayed more overtly. Based on the <italic>recherche de paternit&#x00E9;</italic> and interviews with displaced children 101 interracial relationships in Ruanda-Urundi were identified. In 80 of these cases the couple had a &#x2018;steady&#x2019; relationship, which lasted from several months to years.</p>
<p>Although not explicitly forbidden, interracial relationships in Ruanda-Urundi rarely resulted in marriage. Sometimes, religious authorities conducted ceremonial marriages, but these had no legal standing and few priests were willing to bless the marriages as they generally disapproved of interracial unions. The most common way for Europeans and Africans to publicly acknowledge their unions, was to marry according to customary law.<xref rid="fn21" ref-type="fn"><sup>20</sup></xref> Many relationships between European men and African women were formalised using this traditional marital system, which implied reciprocal rights and obligations. Sometimes the partners lived together in the same house, but more often the <italic>m&#x00E9;nag&#x00E8;re</italic> had her own house where she lived with the children and where the man came to visit.</p>
<p>Often these relationships were initiated without prior consent of the woman or girl involved. Their families married them off after careful deliberation, or they were offered to an honourable guest as a token of hospitality. In some cases the relationship occurred more abruptly and a single sexual encounter led to pregnancy. When interrogated by a state official about the origin of her biracial child, one African woman stated that she was &#x2018;very young at the time, still a virgin, and did not know how to resist a European man that brutal&#x2019;.<xref rid="fn22" ref-type="fn"><sup>21</sup></xref> Another girl claimed that she was taken against her will when visiting her uncle who lived in the <italic>Centre Extra-coutumier</italic>, the African part of new urban areas.<xref rid="fn23" ref-type="fn"><sup>22</sup></xref></p>
<p>However, the image of the interracial relationship as doomed to fail and built on exploitation needs to be balanced with another in which the <italic>m&#x00E9;nag&#x00E8;re</italic> is not just a victim but plays an active role in her own life. The relationships between the parents of the Eurafrican children illustrate that several intimate relationships resulted from love. Both women and men voluntarily started long-lasting relationships with one another that sometimes resulted in multiple children.</p>
<p>The relationships between the parents of the displaced children show that the colonial encounter left room for the self-determination of the women involved. Being the partner of a high official or important agent could endow a woman with a certain level of prestige, allowing her to stand up to traditional authorities and defy existing gender roles. A relationship with a white man could provide extensive economic and social advantages to an African girl, improving the social status of the woman and of her family. The mother of one of the displaced children, for instance, received a house from her European partner, which allowed her a high level of independence, whereas traditionally, women could not possess means of production or own property.<xref rid="fn24" ref-type="fn"><sup>23</sup></xref> By engaging in an interracial relationship a woman could thus surpass certain gender and racial boundaries.</p>
<p>A customary marriage could be dissolved rather easily when one of the partners did not fulfil his or her obligations. Many Europeans undermined the dowry system by using the temporary services of a female companion only to dispose of her when they grew bored or when she fell pregnant. Many women who married European men were chased away when their pregnancies became obvious. This happened so frequently that the authorities spoke of a newfound custom.</p>
<p>Other women, however, chose themselves to end their relationships: one woman filed a complaint against the father of her child because he had embezzled her savings, while another woman left her partner because he did not allow her to dress the way in which she wanted.<xref rid="fn25" ref-type="fn"><sup>24</sup></xref> Both examples indicate that some women made their own choices and stood up to the authority of their European partners.</p>
<p>The mixed-race offspring from these relationships posed a challenge to colonial empires worldwide. Colonial authority was generally based on the supremacy of the European race. People of mixed descent, by their mere existence, undermined this ideological foundation.<xref rid="fn26" ref-type="fn"><sup>25</sup></xref> In Belgian colonial territories, day-to-day life was based on the dichotomy between &#x2018;black&#x2019; and &#x2018;white&#x2019; and although Belgian colonialism did not apply a strict legal apartheid like in South Africa, it employed a colonialism that ordained a <italic>de facto</italic> racial segregation.<xref rid="fn27" ref-type="fn"><sup>26</sup></xref> Consequently, the in-between status of racially ambiguous people posed a political, administrative and juridical problem that led to disputes and controversy at the highest levels of colonial decision-making. Should biracial people be counted as &#x2018;white&#x2019; or &#x2018;black&#x2019;? The so-called &#x2018;<italic>probl&#x00E8;me des mul&#x00E2;tres</italic>&#x2019; or &#x2018;mulatto-problem&#x2019; was born.<xref rid="fn28" ref-type="fn"><sup>27</sup></xref></p>
<p>Because mixed race people&#x2019;s existence was not reflected in colonial legislation, perplexing and diverging debates about the legal status of the <italic>m&#x00E9;tis</italic> within the colony abounded. Depending on the legal recognition by their European progenitor they were Belgian nationals (recognised) or subjects from Congo or Ruanda-Urundi (non-recognised).<xref rid="fn29" ref-type="fn"><sup>28</sup></xref> In reality both recognised an non-recognised <italic>m&#x00E9;tis</italic> occupied a liminal space in colonial society. Belgian authorities strived to create an intermediate group out of the <italic>m&#x00E9;tis</italic> population on its territories. Eurafricans were directed towards technical and go-between professions and encouraged to wed other Eurafricans. Authorities thus hoped to establish a controllable and clearly demarcated group with a distinct place in society. Day to day reality, however, proved to be very different. Eurafricans mingled with African society, penetrated European communities and competed with Africans for jobs.</p>
<p>One of the main facets of the &#x2018;mulatto-problem&#x2019; was the abandonment by their European progenitors. Some European fathers acknowledged their children, but most of them disappeared after their births, leaving mothers to raise the children by themselves. In large parts of Ruanda-Urundi, custom dictated that children be placed in the father&#x2019;s charge. In the case of the children from mixed parentage, with an often-unknown father, this caused a void in the establishment of children&#x2019;s legal custody. This did not necessarily imply that all mixed-race children were abandoned. Most of them were raised by their mothers within the African family unit. Sometimes, however, they occupied a marginal position in these networks, lacking membership claims within this tightly organised structure.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_23519924_00201001_003" sec-type="head1"><title>Displacing Mixed-Race Children: A Colonial Habitude</title>
<sec id="B10.1163_23519924_00201001_004" sec-type="head2"><title>Legal Framework</title>
<p>From the very beginning of Belgian presence in the Congo, authorities established a policy aimed at governing abandoned children and orphans. The policy was inspired by simultaneous evolutions in childcare and the protection of morally abandoned, orphaned or delinquent children in Europe. In this spirit colonial authorities ordered an expansion in accepted guardianship for children born out of wedlock who appeared to be abandoned in the Belgian Congo.<xref rid="fn30" ref-type="fn"><sup>29</sup></xref> After Belgian forces conquered the Ruanda-Urundi territory, the same regulations were applied there. The primary objective of this legislation was to intercede in cases with parents who maltreated or neglected their children, but in a colonial context the legislation was used to install a system that allowed for the physical removal of biracial children from their mothers.</p>
<p>In theory, the label &#x2018;abandoned&#x2019; applied to all children whose fathers and mothers were unknown, as well as children whose parents did not fulfil their tasks of care and support. Mixed-race children did not necessarily fall under this description, but colonial officials were ordered to follow a strict set of regulations concerning children from European descent who did not live with their European parent. The <italic>Recueil &#x00E0; l&#x2019;usage des fonctionnaires et des agents du Service territorial,</italic> a practical manual for colonial officials, instructed agents to actively persuade all African mothers to send their biracial children to the missions and institutions appointed by the state for this purpose and to place them under &#x2018;state guardianship&#x2019;.<xref rid="fn31" ref-type="fn"><sup>30</sup></xref></p>
<p>This state guardianship or <italic>paternit&#x00E9; sociale</italic> was a limited guardianship and did not entail full custody over the children; rather, missions and institutions that were appointed as executive guardians only had the right to exercise certain administrative authority over the education and placement of the children under their care.<xref rid="fn32" ref-type="fn"><sup>31</sup></xref> The legislation concerning abandoned children was described in the decree of 12 July 1890 and eventually collated in the decree of August 4th, 1952 which dictated that the custody of biracial children recognised by their Belgian father ought to be organised by the <italic>Code Civil</italic>, and that non-recognised children, who followed the statute of the autochthon population, depended on the newly installed <italic>commissions de tutelle</italic> or custodial commissions.<xref rid="fn33" ref-type="fn"><sup>32</sup></xref> These commissions entrusted the child to a delegated guardian who vouched for the education of the child. In Ruanda-Urundi, however, the <italic>commissions de tutelle</italic> never functioned appropriately and, consequently, the power to place children under state guardianship was held by the indigenous chief of the territory or the local courts of first instance.<xref rid="fn34" ref-type="fn"><sup>33</sup></xref></p>
<p>As such, mixed-race children all over the Belgian Congo and Ruanda-Urundi were removed from their mothers and placed in state financed institutions. During the colonial presence in Ruanda-Urundi at least 400 children were displaced to institutions. Exact numbers for the displacements in the Belgian Congo are not available but accounts by observers and authorities at the time about the number of mixed-race people allow for a careful estimate of at least a 1000 displaced children.<xref rid="fn35" ref-type="fn"><sup>34</sup></xref> However, the policy was only administered to children who were not legally recognised by their European fathers. Children who were legally recognised by their European fathers remained under his full authority and could be home schooled or attend a school of the father&#x2019;s choice.</p>
<p>In part, this practice came into existence because it was generally assumed that mixed-race children abandoned by their European fathers lived in miserable circumstances. Alphonse Cruyen, a missionary of the Congregation of the Immaculate Heart of Mary (Scheutist fathers) who had been stationed near Leopoldville in the early twentieth century, still believed in 1941 that:
<disp-quote>
<p>Too many [metis] are living in the villages, with their black mother, or if the mother is not there, with an uncle or with the native family. If one has empathy, one feels pity with these little wretches. One sees them everywhere: they drag their miserable little body forth, covered with a cloth, fearful, timid, too afraid even to beg for a look of compassion. They seem to feel that they have no right to exist and that it was wrong to give them life.<xref rid="fn36" ref-type="fn"><sup>35</sup></xref></p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Supposedly, biracial children were not accepted within African communities and therefore needed to be &#x2018;rescued&#x2019;. Policymakers feared that these children would perish if they were left in the care of their indigenous mothers. During the early twentieth century, it was believed that mixed-race girls left in the indigenous society were inclined to sexual indulgence by maternal ancestral influences,<xref rid="fn37" ref-type="fn"><sup>36</sup></xref> while boys risked becoming social outcasts doomed to overthrow colonial authority.<xref rid="fn38" ref-type="fn"><sup>37</sup></xref> These ideas did not only exist in the Belgian Congo and Ruanda-Urundi, but were widespread among various colonial empires. The ideal solution was sought in the removal of the children from the indigenous milieu in order to provide them with an education that would correct their African predisposition and make them culturally European.</p>
<p>Guardianship was generally assigned to institutions and religious missions who took in mixed-race children. In the Congo mixed-race children were sheltered in Boma, Moanda, Lusambo, Luluabourg, Kabare, Kabinda, Kindu, Buta, Ibembo, Lubunda, Lubero, and Bobandana.<xref rid="fn39" ref-type="fn"><sup>38</sup></xref> In Ruanda-Urundi children were sent to the institution for mixed-race children in Save (Astrida territory). The institution was part of the mission of the <italic>S&#x0153;urs missionnaires de Notre-Dame d&#x2019;Afrique (Soeurs Blanches)</italic>, which, since the 1920s, had cared for biracial children from the Ruanda-Urundi region and as of 1946 also from the Kivu region in Belgian Congo.<xref rid="fn40" ref-type="fn"><sup>39</sup></xref>
<fig position="float" id="fig1">
<caption>
<p>Girls at the Save institution during the 1950s (Private collection from the Save Children).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="23519924_002_01_S001_i0001.jpg"/>
</fig>
</p>
<p>As such, many indigenous parents were denied the rights to their children. If a European parent was absent, authorities pressured the African families to bring the child to the institution for mixed-race children in Save and to place the child under state guardianship. This was a job for the territorial agents, who were the heads of colonial authority in each territory of Ruanda-Urundi. Some agents readily fulfilled this task while others resented the policy and condoned the presence of mixed-race children on their territory. Apart from state officials, mothers who desired to keep their children close, needed to be on the lookout for other &#x2018;humanitarians&#x2019; eager to &#x2018;save&#x2019; biracial children from a forlorn future. Only 11 per cent of the children who ended up in the institution for mixed-race children of Save were brought in by their mothers. The other children were either brought to the institution by colonial agents (38 per cent), their fathers (20 per cent), their African families (11 per cent), missionaries (11 per cent) or other passers-by (9 per cent) like European travellers or merchants.<xref rid="fn41" ref-type="fn"><sup>40</sup></xref></p>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_23519924_00201001_005" sec-type="head2"><title>The Save-Institution as a Site of Colonisation</title>
<p>From the 1920s until 1962 some 300 to 400 mixed-race children were placed in the Save-institution.<xref rid="fn42" ref-type="fn"><sup>41</sup></xref> The institution took in children from the age of six but exceptions to this rule were commonplace. Younger children were normally raised at home and sometimes attended classes in the local mission. The girls stayed at Save until they reached the age of majority. The boys attended the mission schools of Nyangezi (Kivu) and, from 1956 onwards, of Byimana (Rwanda) where they took classes alongside African pupils. By the end of the 1950s some of the older girls attended classes in Astrida and Usumbura.</p>
<p>The education of the Eurafrican children was mainly oriented towards their in-between position in African society and cultural elevation. They received a Catholic education that focussed on mathematics, grammar and religion. At an older age, girls received home maintenance courses in order to prepare them for a life as mothers and wives and boys were directed towards technical professions deemed too complicated for Africans. At the same time the education was very European-oriented. Children learned about crops growing in Belgian fields, celebrated Belgian holidays and went on boy-scout-like summer camps just as Belgian children did.</p>
<p>Although institutional policy did not explicitly seek European cultural assimilation, it did pursue the elevation of mixed-race children above African society. As a result, children who spent their whole lives in the institution gradually withdrew from their mothers and their African roots. Marianne, one of the Save-girls, regretfully remembered how she and her friends regarded their mothers with sardonic disapproval when they came to visit: &#x2018;Often we were not nice to her, because she was black, we did not like our mothers. We were embarrassed that they were black.&#x2019;<xref rid="fn43" ref-type="fn"><sup>42</sup></xref>
<fig position="float" id="fig2">
<caption>
<p>Save&#x2019;s Girls refectory late 1950s. Private Collection from the Save Children</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="23519924_002_01_S001_i0002.jpg"/>
</fig></p>
<p>Maria Neys, one of the oldest pupils in the institution, and Sister Lutgardis, head mistress of the institution during the second half of the 1950s, both stated that African mothers rarely came to visit even if they lived in the vicinity.<xref rid="fn44" ref-type="fn"><sup>43</sup></xref> Mothers who did visit their children, however, were allowed only short visits and unlike European fathers they were not always warmly received. Charlie, one of the displaced children, remembers that &#x2018;the mothers were discouraged to come, after a couple of times they stopped coming.&#x2019; He remembers that the contact between the children and their mothers was impeded in multiple ways: &#x2018;I remember, when I arrived, I spoke Kinyarwanda, which was forbidden at the institution. I needed to learn how to speak French as soon as possible. They tried to completely detach us from our roots.&#x2019;<xref rid="fn45" ref-type="fn"><sup>44</sup></xref></p>
<p>Gradually, a physical, emotional and linguistic distance between the children and their African kin occurred. The segregation from their mothers led many children to believe they had been abandoned, even if they had not. Contact with the surrounding African society was minimal and often difficult, which in part explains why few children objected to their later move to Belgium and even pictured Belgium as a promised land.<xref rid="fn46" ref-type="fn"><sup>45</sup></xref> Nonetheless, the trauma of the separation from their mothers was profound, especially for the little ones. Many felt homesick, depressed and lonely. Some tried fleeing the institution only to be retrieved, punished and subjected to even more vigorous attempts to assimilate them with their European roots.<xref rid="fn47" ref-type="fn"><sup>46</sup></xref> As such, confinement in the institution functioned as a vector of colonisation and damaged the intimate ties of the children with their families and homeland.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_23519924_00201001_006" sec-type="head1"><title>A Second Displacement<xref rid="fn48" ref-type="fn"><sup>47</sup></xref></title>
<sec id="B10.1163_23519924_00201001_007" sec-type="head2"><title>The &#x2018;European Dream&#x2019; of Sister Lutgardis</title>
<p>Upon her installation as head mistress of the institution for mixed-race children in Save in 1955, Sister Lutgardis started to imagine that the eventual aim of the institution ought to be the preparation of the children for a transfer to Europe.<xref rid="fn49" ref-type="fn"><sup>48</sup></xref> She believed that mixed-race children had no future in post-independence Ruanda-Urundi for several reasons. During the 1950s the Save-institution had become overpopulated and lodged up to 120 children though it was barely equipped to host 90 pupils. As only a few fathers paid tuition fees for their children, the institution depended heavily on governmental support. In the last years before independence, however, financing decreased, while increasing numbers of children necessitated more dormitories, classrooms and modern facilities including running water and electricity.</p>
<p>Moreover, Sister Lutgardis believed an extra school for boys was highly needed, since boys were only allowed at Save until they reached the age of 12 years. Afterwards, they moved to Nyangezi or Byimana, where they could not always stay full-time. Hence, during school vacations the boys returned to their African families or roamed the hillsides until the school gates re-opened. Sister Lutgardis and her associates feared that these boys would &#x2018;fall back&#x2019; into the local societies. The same fear existed for the older girls. The educational system in the Belgian colonial area had focused on quantity rather than quality. During the 1950s higher education was still in its infancy and few options existed for mixed-race youth who successfully finished their secondary schooling. This inevitably implied that the Save-institution faced a grim challenge each year in trying to find suitable positions for its graduated pupils. Some worked for Europeans and married other Eurafricans but others, despite the mission&#x2019;s efforts, returned to their African kin.</p>
<p>In 1959, the Save-institution also received a visit from two members of the <italic>Conseil Sup&#x00E9;rieur du Pays</italic>, the highest indigenous representative council of the country, who informed Sister Lutgardis that they did not intend to continue the adapted education for mixed-race children after independence.<xref rid="fn50" ref-type="fn"><sup>49</sup></xref> In a 1973 television interview Sister Lutgardis explained that the Mwami, the Rwandese king, had told her that he did not intend doing anything for the children after independence.<xref rid="fn51" ref-type="fn"><sup>50</sup></xref> The reactions of these Rwandan dignitaries kept Sister Lutgardis guessing about the future of the biracial children. As one of the mission&#x2019;s objectives was to preserve the children for the Catholic faith, Sister Lutgardis dreaded that children would be placed in neutral institutions upon independence. She believed that only a timely evacuation could provide continuity in the children&#x2019;s Catholic education and prevent them from returning to indigenous society.<xref rid="fn52" ref-type="fn"><sup>51</sup></xref></p>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_23519924_00201001_008" sec-type="head2"><title>Rising Tension and Social Revolt</title>
<p>On the eve of independence, Sister Lutgardis started lobbying for the evacuation of the children more intensely, due to the rising tension within Rwandese society. Social and political tensions, which had been growing during the colonial period, found their release in a social upheaval that revolutionised traditional power structures in the country. The preferential treatment of Tutsi over Hutu by the Belgian colonial administration underlay a slow &#x2018;Tutsification&#x2019; of command in Rwanda: Tutsi enjoyed various advantages in education and employment ensuring their presence in executive positions. This policy led to a strengthening of the position of local (Tutsi-)chiefs while simultaneously eroding the protective nature of the relationship between the chief and his (Hutu-)subjects.<xref rid="fn53" ref-type="fn"><sup>52</sup></xref> In 1959 the oppressed (Hutu-)majority revolted against the (Tutsi-)elites and ethnic violence between Hutu and Tutsi stirred every day live in the mandate area.<xref rid="fn54" ref-type="fn"><sup>53</sup></xref></p>
<p>The Save-hill did not escape this wave of violence. Being the birthplace of Joseph Gitera, the first president of the <sc>aprosoma</sc>-movement and co-author of the Hutu-manifesto, the hill was used as a strategic rampart for the revolutionaries.<xref rid="fn55" ref-type="fn"><sup>54</sup></xref> Its central positioning in the Astrida territory also made it an ideal locus for confrontation. Furthermore, Astrida held symbolic value as the centre of Tutsi-power and the court of the Mwami traditionally resided there. The mixed-race children, who lived on the Save-hill, could not be categorised easily, which was problematic in a society that increasingly defined itself according to ethnical and social divisions. Accordingly, Sister Lutgardis began to fear not only for the well-being and religious orientation of the children in the institution, but for their lives as well.</p>
<p>Indeed, several displaced children testify that biracial people occupied a delicate position in Ruanda-Urundi, even before the ethnic tension increased. When the children left the institution to go to church in Save, the <italic>Banyarwanda</italic> shouted at them, pelted them with stones and dirt and pulled their hair.<xref rid="fn56" ref-type="fn"><sup>55</sup></xref> The rising tension between the Hutu and the Tutsi in 1959 and in subsequent years, enlarged the perceived threat against children of mixed descent. Sister Lutgardis believed that the mixed-race children, who fell in between different categorisations, were in a very vulnerable position. Additionally, more than 85 per cent of the mixed-race children housed in the institution supposedly had Tutsi mothers, which made their presence more delicate in the ethnically torn Rwanda-region where Tutsi-elites were hunted down and assassinated on a daily basis.<xref rid="fn57" ref-type="fn"><sup>56</sup></xref> In effect many Tutsi-family members of mixed-race children lost their lives during the revolution, while even more fell victim to death squads and <italic>Interahamwe</italic> during the 1994 genocide.</p>
<p>Despite this threat, not all missionaries shared Lutgardis&#x2019;s opinion that the displacement of the children to Belgium was a matter of life and death. Sister Maria Andrea, a young Belgian novice at the Save mission felt that, even though the mixed-race children were not loved in Africa, they never were in direct danger.<xref rid="fn58" ref-type="fn"><sup>57</sup></xref></p>
<p>The social revolution served as a catalyst for the transfer of the children. However, it remains unclear to what degree the Tutsi ancestry of the children was an actual motivator. Arguably, the children&#x2019;s mixed descent literally placed them &#x2018;outside&#x2019; of society. According to one of the older girls who inhabited Save at the end of the 1950s the mixed-race children were not ethnically but racially categorised:
<disp-quote>
<p>The blacks did not think of us as blacks, to them we were 100 per cent white. We were the children of the white men, the <italic>bazungus</italic>, all white. So the problem of Tutsi or Hutu did not pose itself in our case.<xref rid="fn59" ref-type="fn"><sup>58</sup></xref></p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Mixed-race people were not directly involved in the struggle between the Tutsi and the Hutu but they were vulnerable as a minority and Sister Lutgardis believed it was hard to predict which side the revolutionaries would take regarding the children. Furthermore, one should not forget that the revolution of 1959 was a social revolution of the oppressed majority against the established elites. Although the European coloniser chose the side of the Hutus in the hope of preserving its powerbase in the region, mixed-race people had enjoyed a preferential treatment by the colonial authorities and it was not unthinkable that the masses would turn against them. In this turbulent context, Sister Lutgardis did not anticipate a prosperous future for mixed-race children in Africa. Even if the threat of the revolution was not as large as she believed, she used the revolution as a rationale to hasten the evacuation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_23519924_00201001_009" sec-type="head2"><title>Cooperation of the Colonial Government</title>
<p>Sister Lutgardis decided to bring the matter to the attention of the Belgian political authorities. In March 1960 she wrote to the newly installed Catholic Minister of Belgian Congo and Ruanda-Urundi, August De Schryver, who she had met during his earlier visit to the region: &#x2018;There should be action at any cost, our children are threatened with death on a daily basis by the natives, their lives which were difficult already, now have become even more grim.&#x2019;<xref rid="fn60" ref-type="fn"><sup>59</sup></xref> De Schryver agreed to finance the transportation of the children to Belgium based on the humanitarian nature of the undertaking and the recognition that biracial children endangered social order in the turbulent region.<xref rid="fn61" ref-type="fn"><sup>60</sup></xref> Seemingly, the colonial government itself never made plans to transplant the children to Europe as in 1959 they promised the Save mission the funds for the construction of a second dormitory that could shelter an additional 60 children.<xref rid="fn62" ref-type="fn"><sup>61</sup></xref></p>
<p>However, colonial authorities felt a sense of responsibility for the biracial children. After all, they were children of European descent who had been torn away from their families and the indigenous milieu by colonial officials. Because of their placement in the Save institution, most of these children had no network to which to return. Save and the other mixed-race children had become their home and principal family. At Save, Byimana and Nyangezi the children had received an adapted education which would have made it particularly hard to reintegrate into African society. The feeling that it would be cruel and even unthinkable to abandon the children at the moment of independence prompted the authorities to consider Sister Lutgardis&#x2019;s call for evacuation. The subsequent displacements were grounded in the belief that the children had to be protected from a native society that was considered unwilling and ill-suited to raise Eurafrican children.</p>
<p>By the time the government agreed to finance the transportation, 23 children had already been evacuated at the instigation of Sister Lutgardis.<xref rid="fn63" ref-type="fn"><sup>62</sup></xref> She received help from several charitable organisations such as the Ruandafund, the <italic>Association Pour la Protection des Mul&#x00E2;tres</italic> (<sc>appm</sc>) and the Adoption work of Th&#x00E9;r&#x00E8;se Wante.<xref rid="fn64" ref-type="fn"><sup>63</sup></xref> The first group of children was evacuated on 4 November 1959. From that moment on, small groups of children departed for Belgium, filling leftover seats on flights that evacuated Europeans fleeing the region. Occasionally, larger numbers of children were evacuated on Sobelair charter flights and military airplanes.<xref rid="fn65" ref-type="fn"><sup>64</sup></xref> By the summer of 1962, the 124 children from the Save-institution had left for Belgium along with large numbers of mixed-race children residing in nearby schools in Byimana, Nyangezi and urban centres like Bukavu, Kigali and Usumbura, adding up to a total of 283 children.</p>
<p>The situation in the Belgian Congo was of a different nature. A large-scale removal like that in Ruanda-Urundi was never organised. This can partially be explained by the specific political situation in both regions. Congo decolonised very suddenly as opposed to the relatively long march towards independence in Ruanda-Urundi. There was no time to organise an evacuation. At the same time an evacuation may have seemed less necessary. Indeed, throughout the colonial period the position of Eurafricans seemed to have been more problematic in Ruanda-Urundi then it was in the Congo were mixed-race children mingled easier and more freely with the African population. The institutionalisation of mixed race children was not as strict as in Ruanda-Urundi. The fact that the <italic>m&#x00E9;tis</italic> were not well liked in Ruanda-Urundi combined with the ethnic violence in the region were important motivators for evacuation.<xref rid="fn66" ref-type="fn"><sup>65</sup></xref></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_23519924_00201001_010" sec-type="head1"><title>Strategies of Resistance</title>
<p>In the following section I will illustrate how the mothers reacted to the removal of their children. Some mothers agreed with the displacement while others passionately fought against it. I will show that mothers applied different strategies of resistance, which authorities successfully counteracted.</p>
<sec id="B10.1163_23519924_00201001_011" sec-type="head2"><title>Disparate Reactions</title>
<p>Some mothers, like many Europeans, believed that the mixed-race children did not belong in indigenous society. One child&#x2019;s family explained that they were not forced to bring the girl to Save:
<disp-quote>
<p>It was not forced. She was too white. She could not stay there and it bothered everyone, including the mother, [&#x2026;] she was too much like the whites.<xref rid="fn67" ref-type="fn"><sup>66</sup></xref></p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Some mothers wanted to send their children to Save and even fought to do so. At the school, the children received a European-inspired upbringing, they were guaranteed a roof over their heads and compared to their African counterparts they enjoyed a rich and diverse diet. Thus, placing their children in institutions like Save was a strategy poor mothers applied in the hope to ensure a better future for their offspring. The existence of this strategy supports the notion that African mothers actively engaged in securing the best they could for their children. Most mothers, indeed, did not protest when the authorities ordered to bring their children to the Save-institution.</p>
<p>At times, however, African parents objected to the displacement. Some mothers tried to hide their children by keeping them inside for months or even years. Other children, whose skin and hair were dark enough, were mingled with the indigenous children in the hope that Europeans passing through would not notice them. A mother of two mixed-race girls and one boy opposed the displacement of her children. After the death of her European companion this woman raised the children on her own. She had lived with her European partner for several years and the man had legally recognised the children. When he died, the woman no longer had the means to provide for her children. Shortly after the father&#x2019;s death, state officials drafted a scathing report criticising the scantily clad children, the poor state of the hut they lived in and the heap of dried banana leaves that passed for a bed, none of which were deemed suited to raise Eurafrican children. The father&#x2019;s custodial rights had passed to one of his European friends and as soon as this man read the report, he decided to place the children in Save. Despite the mother&#x2019;s vigorous protests, state officials took the children.<xref rid="fn68" ref-type="fn"><sup>67</sup></xref></p>
<p>The situation was altogether different if the European parent took charge of his or her offspring. The mere presence of a European father, even if he did not legally recognise his children, insured his paternal authority: he decided on the education of the child. The situation was slightly different when the mother was European. The colonial authorities of Ruanda-Urundi recorded only five cases in which the mothers were white and the fathers were black. In all off these cases the mothers were very young (fourteen to nineteen years old) and their families exercised immediate and strong pressure to place the child in an institution. Families and missionaries alike argued that the women&#x2019;s chances of marriage were eliminated and their social positions marginalised. Nevertheless, they were encouraged to legally recognise their children. This way, these European women, and not the children&#x2019;s indigenous fathers, could decide over the fate of the child.</p>
<p>When the moment arrived to displace the children to Belgium, government officials realised that a more solid base than the state guardianship was necessary in order to authorise for the children&#x2019;s departure. The state guardianship allowed for simple administrative actions but did not go as far as emancipating the children or authorising a foreign displacement for a period of more than three months.<xref rid="fn69" ref-type="fn"><sup>68</sup></xref> State officials were therefore instructed to track down the mothers in order to persuade them to let their children leave for Belgium.</p>
<p>The officials relentlessly tried to convince the mothers. They stated that the children belonged to them; that, in essence, they were European. One mother remembers that the authorities told her that, because she was not married to the father of her child, the child automatically became an &#x2018;orphan&#x2019; and that the child did not belong to her.<xref rid="fn70" ref-type="fn"><sup>69</sup></xref> Often these mothers, being poor African women, did not feel as if they were in a position to refuse the demands of high-ranking colonial agents. When interviewed today, a maternal uncle of a displaced boy testified:
<disp-quote>
<p>When the agents came to get him, the mother did not have the means to take care of him so the arguments were easily made. They said: &#x2018;we will take care of him&#x2019; [&#x2026;]. She gave her child because she did not have the means to raise her children.<xref rid="fn71" ref-type="fn"><sup>70</sup></xref></p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>The removal was presented as necessary to secure the children&#x2019;s future. In Belgium they would receive a suitable education, allowing them to find respectable jobs and provide economic prosperity for the whole family upon their return to Africa.</p>
<p>This line of reasoning drove the majority of the mothers to &#x2018;voluntarily&#x2019; sign a <italic>d&#x00E9;claration d&#x2019;accord.</italic> In doing so they placed their child under the supervision of the state and designated charitable organisations and allowed their children to go to Belgium in order to finish their education. Many of the mothers could not read or write and had no real understanding of the papers they signed with a thumb-mark.</p>
<p>The authorisation the mothers signed did, however, not completely waive their parental rights. In theory they reserved the right to revoke their decision, which implied that the charitable institutions that took on the children in Belgium only had <italic>de facto</italic> guardianship over the children.<xref rid="fn72" ref-type="fn"><sup>71</sup></xref> Once in Belgium, however, all ties with Africa were cut. When a displaced man contacted his mother for the first time in 1987, after having learnt that unlike what he had been told, she was not dead, his mother reportedly cried out: &#x2018;Have you finally finished your education?&#x2019;<xref rid="fn73" ref-type="fn"><sup>72</sup></xref> She had been waiting for him this whole time. Indeed, most mothers assumed their children would return, therefore only a handful had agreed to sign adoption papers. A few mothers had signed adoption papers, but most of the mothers resolutely refused this, and therefore state officials soon stopped trying and only asked the mothers to sign the <italic>d&#x00E9;claration d&#x2019;accord</italic> which was necessary to get the children out of the country.</p>
<p>Some of the older girls and boys desired to leave, even though their parents resisted the transfer. Jeanne, sixteen at the time of the evacuation, remembers that her mother dreaded her departure:
<disp-quote>
<p>The mothers had to sign but <italic>maman</italic> never wanted to. She did not want me to go away. [&#x2026;] I asked her myself: &#x2018;<italic>Maman</italic>, all the others have left, why can&#x2019;t you sign?&#x2019;<xref rid="fn74" ref-type="fn"><sup>73</sup></xref></p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Jeanne wanted to leave for Belgium just like her friends had done. She no longer wanted to live with her mother, who she believed had abandoned her. She had grown up at the institution; the other mixed-race boys and girls had become her family. Without consent of her mother, Jeanne left for Belgium anyhow.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_23519924_00201001_012" sec-type="head2"><title>Agreeing to Disagree?</title>
<p>Not all mothers, however, obediently acquiesced. The extraordinary circumstances of the transfer forced some mothers to transcend their traditional roles. In a society where African women stood at the bottom of social hierarchy, several mothers defied the orders of colonial officials and persisted in their refusal. At least 17 women vigorously contested their children&#x2019;s displacement.<xref rid="fn75" ref-type="fn"><sup>74</sup></xref> All kinds of strategies were deployed in often-useless attempts to prevent the transfer. Lionel remembers his mother coming over to visit him one last time in Byimana:
<disp-quote>
<p>I remember very well, when we were ready to go to Belgium, I was in Byimana and the evening they were supposed to come and pick me up to drive me to the airport, my mother came visiting. She came and she asked the missionaries: &#x2018;can I take Lionel with me? I want to buy him some clothes&#x2019;.<xref rid="fn76" ref-type="fn"><sup>75</sup></xref></p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>When Lionel visited his mother years later, she told him she intended to take him home with her during this last shopping spree but that the missionaries had not allowed it.</p>
<p>Some mothers tried to hide their children who had not yet reached the age to enter the Save-institution. Marguerite remembers:
<disp-quote>
<p>When the Belgians had to leave, they gathered their children all around. To prevent them from taking my child, I hid him, cut his hair, because he had too much hair. However, the hair grew back over-night, which was annoying.<xref rid="fn77" ref-type="fn"><sup>76</sup></xref></p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Some mothers called upon their European acquaintances in a desperate attempt to undo the decision to evacuate their children. Tina asked her former employee, Madame M.V.G. to intervene and ask Sister Lurgardis if her child could stay in Rwanda. M.V.G. wrote to Sister Lutgardis:
<disp-quote>
<p>I write to you to ask for help for the poor Tina who will hand you this letter. She came to me, crying out of pure misery. [&#x2026;] I gave her the money to make the journey to Save so she could see her child once more. She would very much like to have the child closer to her. Because she is Rwandese I believe it would be better to make the child live in Rwanda.<xref rid="fn78" ref-type="fn"><sup>77</sup></xref></p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Other mothers wrote to the authorities in their own name, often supported by their families and indigenous husbands:
<disp-quote>
<p>I have the honour to inform you that my wife and I do not agree with the transfer away from us to Belgium of the child, which is only 7 years and a few months old. We would love to see the child continue his studies at Save, where his mother will have the opportunity to visit him whenever possible.<xref rid="fn79" ref-type="fn"><sup>78</sup></xref></p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Several mothers demanded concrete assurances and tried introducing conditions before they were willing to allow the displacement of their child:
<disp-quote>
<p>I do not wish my child to go to Belgium. I am greatly thankful to mister administrator of the territory for his efforts but I ask him if he would be as kind as to place the child in any school in Ruanda. The daughter that my big sister had with the same man, has been in Belgium for 25 years. I do not wish to see the same thing happening to my girl. I will only allow my child&#x2019;s departure if her father acknowledges her.<xref rid="fn80" ref-type="fn"><sup>79</sup></xref></p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Other mothers uttered more modest requests such as being allowed to say goodbye to their children, or to get information about the future whereabouts of their children. One mother agreed that a displacement to Europe had many advantages but wanted to ensure the bond with her child. A European official, representing another anxious mother, wrote in support of her refusal to let her child go:
<disp-quote>
<p>The refusal should not be interpreted as bad will from her part. She is an intelligent woman who understands very well where lie the real interests of her child. But this matter of departure to Europe and adoption are too vague to appease her motherly apprehensions.<xref rid="fn81" ref-type="fn"><sup>80</sup></xref></p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>These simple requests were seldom accommodated. Mothers who were promised a last goodbye often travelled to Save in vain, finding an empty institution upon their arrival.</p>
<p>The various protests against the transfer and the demands for guarantees indicate that, contrary to what the official institutions and missionaries claimed, these mothers did take a real interest in their children. The depiction of the evacuation as being a necessity in order to save the children from neglect and abandonment is thus inaccurate and incomplete.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_23519924_00201001_013" sec-type="head2"><title>Neutralising the Objections</title>
<p>Despite these protests, returning children to their mothers was not considered an option as this ran counter to all existing philosophies and policies concerning biracial children. Missionaries dreaded the pernicious effects of indigenous society on the children&#x2019;s intellectual maturity and religious dedication. They showed little understanding for the motives of mothers who wanted to keep their children close. In an attempt to invalidate the mother&#x2019;s claims to their children they were blamed of being overly sentimental, sordid, selfish and short-sighted and accused of being unfit mothers altogether.<xref rid="fn82" ref-type="fn"><sup>81</sup></xref></p>
<p>The refusals posed a challenge to the administrative powers because they jeopardised the evacuation of the children. When a mother did not agree to the transfer, authorities administered great pressure, resorting to more repressive means in order to convince her. Mothers who pertinently refused to sign the authorisation received a letter from the colonial administration billing them for the cost of the education and maintenance dispended during the child&#x2019;s stay in Save. In these letters the mothers were blamed for lacking interest in their children. If a mother could pay the bill for past and future costs, the child could stay in Save or in another African institution. If she failed to respond to the letter within the period of one month, the custody over her child was shifted to the state and a newly appointed guardian decided if the child was to be brought to Belgium.<xref rid="fn83" ref-type="fn"><sup>82</sup></xref></p>
<p>None of the mothers could afford the sum. Hence, they were passively coerced to let their children leave for Belgium. Not all mothers, however, were swayed. One mother confirmed that:
<disp-quote>
<p>[&#x2026;] she will maintain refusing if she does not get the address where her child will reside in Belgium. In relation to the cost of the stay of her child in Save, she said with a little peal of laughter, that she will do whatever she can in order to pay it.<xref rid="fn84" ref-type="fn"><sup>83</sup></xref></p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>A third option, which was not explicitly mentioned in the letter, existed as well: three mothers chose to come and pick up their child, two of whom eventually gave in to the pressure and let their child leave for Belgium regardless.</p>
<p>Mothers who refused were not the only obstacles to the children&#x2019;s displacement. Many mothers could not be located: some had moved, while others were dead. In these cases, a clever administrative move ensured the transfer of the child. On 5 December 1959 a <italic>Jugement Coutumier</italic> (customary ruling) of the local court of first instance, following Rwandese customary law, dictated that if the legal guardian of the children could not be located, guardianship could be transferred to a third party. Consequently, the court of first instance in Astrida issued numerous rulings diverting the guardianship of the children to local chiefs or Sister Lutgardis, thus successfully circumventing the mothers. However, it should be noted that these rulings, like the <italic>d&#x00E9;claration d&#x2019;accord</italic>, did not remove the custody African mothers had over their children; they merely installed a non-custodial guardianship in order to successfully move the children to Belgium.</p>
<p>As such, the displacement of the Eurafrican children from Ruanda-Urundi provides an unprecedented perspective on the tension between colonial suppression and indigenous resistance in an intimate panorama. Mothers tried to outsmart the colonial government by hiding their children, enlisting European friends, adding conditions to their departure, begging or simply refusing to let their children go. The colonial authorities countered most strategies using both European and customary law as they saw fit. Although the mothers never lost full custody of their children, their inferior position within colonial society ensured that they could seldom effectively claim this right. Once in Belgium, the separation was consolidated by the fact that several foster families obtained the legal guardianship over the child assigned to them. Families did so by using the system of the <italic>familieraad</italic> (family counsel). The family counsel aimed to fill the void in the guardianship over children who did not have a father or a mother, children whose parents were not able to state their wishes or children whose parents were absent, like the Save children. A family counsel traditionally existed out of six family members. In the case of the Eurafrican children, a family counsel was composed out of &#x2018;friends&#x2019; and people who knew the child. This could be the foster family or social workers from the charitable organisations that had helped with the evacuation. Few children ever returned to Africa.</p>
<p>So although African women showed power and self-determination in their encounters with European men, when it came to their mixed-race progeny, indigenous women often had very little voice. Many mothers passively consented to the displacement of their children in the hope to let them escape a life of poverty. Others were coerced.</p>
<p>The tactics the mothers used bear witness to their efforts to disrupt the unilateral decision-making of colonial society in order to break free from their ordained role as &#x2018;subjects&#x2019; who passively submitted to colonisation. The practical strategy adopted in response to these refusals was to simply overrule the mothers&#x2019; common-law rights over their children by making the state or people and institutions appointed by the state the legal guardian of all children of mixed descent. By doing so, Belgian colonial powers instrumentalised civic and customary law, manipulating indigenous codes of conduct to their advantage.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="head1" id="B10.1163_23519924_00201001_014"><title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Although the &#x2018;evacuated&#x2019; children only comprised a fraction of all mixed-race people living in Belgian colonial territories, their displacement is symbolic of the attitude that colonial powers adopted toward mixed-race populations. The treatment of this relatively small group and the efforts that were taken to demarcate their &#x2018;appropriate&#x2019; position in the social order are indicative of the symbolic importance of mixed-race people within Belgian colonial society. The removal of the Save children from their families during colonial times can, just like other child removals within colonial or imperial contexts, be seen as a strategy adopted by the dominant authorities to exert their power, reinforce their ranks and discipline peripheral groups.<xref rid="fn85" ref-type="fn"><sup>84</sup></xref></p>
<p>Indeed, Belgian colonial authorities strived to create an ideal society with strictly demarcated and controllable groups. Institutionalising the children disciplined the mothers who had crossed racial boundaries and were seen as a negative influence on the children. Placing the children in institutions removed them from everyday society in which they might cause confusion or instigate revolt. At the same time officials hoped to make the children into an in-between class able to provide supportive tasks within colonial society, trained to spread a western way of life and colonise the intimate sphere. However, instead of being a bridge between coloniser and colonised, concentrating the children isolated them from African society in the colony and condemned them to a position in-between the two groups.</p>
<p>At the moment of decolonisation, this in-between position became a key problem. The children did not have a place in indigenous society. The direction of the institution believed that the children had become a group &#x2018;at risk&#x2019; and hazardous in a troublesome region, as they were living proof of Belgian favouritism. They were convinced that the children belonged in Europe. The institution urged for the children&#x2019;s removal from the region and requested aid from the Belgian authorities in doing so. Mothers contested the removal, which was based on the premise that they abandoned their children when in fact the children were abandoned by their European fathers. The policy and discourse of the removal reduced the mothers to bad, unloving and unfit mothers. The small scale and largely failing tactics they applied hoping to keep their children were their sole means of countering this colonial discourse.</p>
<p>The controversy around the children&#x2019;s removal arises from their in-between position as culturally European but legally African. The religious institutions and colonial authorities believed that the &#x2018;natural position&#x2019; of the children was in European society, regardless their legal affiliation. Unlike non-recognised mixed race groups in Dutch and English colonies and even in Congo, the non-recognised mixed race population of Ruanda-Urundi was seen as an integral part of the European society. In this respect the practice of the displacement of the <italic>m&#x00E9;tis</italic> from Ruanda-Urundi diverges from the official Belgian position towards mixed-race populations. Access to Belgian citizenship (and consequently Belgium itself) was exclusively dependant on legal recognition by the European parent. Without this recognition, even if the child was in the European sphere of influence, Belgian citizenship could not be claimed, and in theory the child was considered African. Therefore removing these children from African society was perceived as highly controversial.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn id="fn2">
<p>1&#x2002;L. De Witte, <italic>The assassination of Lumumba</italic> (London and New York 2001); A. Hochschild, <italic>King Leopold&#x2019;s ghost: A story of greed, terror, and heroism in colonial Africa</italic> (London 2002).</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn3">
<p>2&#x2002;V. Beel, &#x2018;Waarheidscommissie nodig voor "bastaards van kolonie"&#x2019;, <italic>De Standaard</italic>, 16 June 2010.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn4">
<p>3&#x2002;The case of the forced placement of the mixed race children was, among others, subject of a hearing in front of the Flemish Parliament (28 January 2015) concerning forced adoptions in Belgium which led up to the public apology by the Parliament on 24 November 24 2015.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn5">
<p>4&#x2002;Ann Laura Stoler, &#x2018;Sexual affronts and racial frontiers: European identities and the cultural politics of exclusion in colonial Southeast Asia&#x2019;, <italic>Comparative Studies in Society and History</italic> 34:3 (1992) 514&#x2013;551: 524&#x2013;526; Julia Clancy-Smith and Frances Gouda, <italic>Domesticating the empire: race, gender, and family life in French and Dutch colonialism</italic> (Charlottesville <sc>va</sc>, 1998); Ann Laura Stoler, <italic>Carnal knowledge and imperial power: race and the intimate in colonial rule</italic> (Berkeley 2002) 119&#x2013;121.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn6">
<p>5&#x2002;J. Cot&#x00E9;, &#x2018;"The sins of their fathers": culturally at risk children and the colonial state in Asia&#x2019;, <italic>Paedagogica Historica: International Journal of the History of Education</italic> 45:1&#x2013;2 (2009) 129&#x2013;142.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn7">
<p>6&#x2002;C. Paris, <italic>De la condition juridique des m&#x00E9;tis dans les colonies et possessions fran&#x00E7;aises: des m&#x00E9;tis franco-annamites de l&#x2019;Indo-Chine</italic> (Paris 1904); P. Guillaume, &#x2018;Les m&#x00E9;tis en Indochine&#x2019;, <italic>Annales de d&#x00E9;mographie historique</italic> (1995) 185&#x2013;195; O. White, <italic>Children of the French Empire. Miscegenation and colonial society in French West Africa 1895&#x2013;1960</italic> (Oxford 1999); E. Saada, <italic>Les enfants de la colonie: les m&#x00E9;tis de l&#x2019;Empire fran&#x00E7;ais entre suj&#x00E9;tion et citoyennet&#x00E9;</italic> (Paris 2007); C.E. Firpo, &#x2018;Lost boys: "Abandoned" Eurasian children and the management of the racial topography in colonial Indochina, 1938&#x2013;1945&#x2019;, <italic>French Colonial History</italic> 8 (2007) 203&#x2013;221; J.A. Boittin, C. Firpo, and E.M. Church, &#x2018;Hierarchies of race and gender in the French colonial empire, 1914&#x2013;1946&#x2019;, <italic>Historical Reflections</italic> 37:1 (2011) 60&#x2013;90.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn8">
<p>7&#x2002;B. Crosette, <italic>The great hill stations of Asia</italic> (Boulder 1998); D. Kennedy, <italic>The magic mountains. Hill stations of the British Raj</italic> (Berkeley 1996); T.J. Wilson, <italic>In the best interest of the child? Stolen children: aboriginal pain/white shame</italic> (Canberra 1997); S. Sen, <italic>Colonial childhoods. The juvenile periphery of India 1850&#x2013;1945</italic> (London 2005); M.D. Jacobs, <italic>White mother to a dark race: settler colonialism, materialism, and the removal of indigenous children in the American West and Australia, 1880&#x2013;1940</italic> (Lincoln 2009).</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn9">
<p>8&#x2002;C. Firpo, &#x2018;Crises of Whiteness and Empire in colonial Indochina: the removal of abandoned Eurasian children from the Vietnamese milieu, 1890&#x2013;1956&#x2019;, <italic>Journal of Social History</italic> 43:3 (2010) 587&#x2013;613; Y. Den&#x00E9;ch&#x00E8;re, &#x2018;Les &#x2018;rapatriements&#x2019; en France des enfants eurasiens de l&#x2019;ex-Indochine. Pratiques, d&#x00E9;bats, m&#x00E9;moires&#x2019;, <italic>Enfances d&#x00E9;plac&#x00E9;es en situation coloniale, Revue d&#x2019;histoire de l&#x2019;enfance "irr&#x00E9;guli&#x00E8;re"</italic> 14 (2012) 123&#x2013;139.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn10">
<p>9&#x2002;C. Laarman, <italic>Oude onbekenden. Het politieke en publieke debat over postkoloniale migranten, 1945&#x2013;2005</italic> (Hilversum 2013) 57, 65&#x2013;74.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn11">
<p>10&#x2002;E.R. Delooz, &#x2018;De oase der Naamlozen&#x2019;, <italic>De vrouw in middenstand en burgerij</italic> 4 (April 1959) 4&#x2013;6.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn12">
<p>11&#x2002;Testimonies can be found in: <italic>Kazungu, le m&#x00E9;tis</italic>, Documentary by Georges Kamanayo, 52&#x2019;, 1999; <italic>Bulaya, qu&#x2019;as-tu fait de mon enfant?</italic> Documentary by Lydia Ngaruko, 47&#x2019;, 2004; Kathleen Ghequiere and Sibo Kanobana, <italic>De bastaards van onze kolonie. Verzwegen verhalen van Belgische metissen</italic> (Brussel 2010); <italic>Bons Baisers de la Colonie</italic>, Documentary by Nathalie Borgers, 74&#x2019;, 2011; Enfants Mul&#x00E2;tres de Save, radiobroadcast by Aline Wavreille, <sc>rtbf</sc>, Transversales, 28 May 2011.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn13">
<p>12&#x2002;As ordered by the decree of 5 July 1948, which came into force at 5 April 1949 in Ruanda-Urundi. With this decree, the legislator wanted to diminish the number of non-&#x00AD;recognized mixed-race children that depended on state support.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn14">
<p>13&#x2002;Files concerning this <italic>recherche de paternit&#x00E9;</italic> can be found in the individual dossiers of mixed-race children that form the contents of the <italic>Archives du Ruanda-Urundi d&#x2019;un caract&#x00E8;re d&#x00E9;licat</italic> (<sc>rwabu</sc>) (A61) held at the African Archives of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Brussels, Belgium). The exact file numbers will further be referred to as: <sc>rwabu</sc> file number.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn15">
<p>14&#x2002;Archives concerning the displacement of the mixed-race children of the Ruanda-Urundi can be found in the African Archives of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Brussels, Belgium), the Archive of the <italic>Association pour la protection des mul&#x00E2;tres</italic> (<sc>appm</sc>) held at the Royal Museum of Central Africa (Tervuren, Belgium), the archive of the <italic>Ruandafonds</italic> - <italic>Christelijke Middenstands en Burgervrouwen</italic> held at <sc>kadoc</sc> (Leuven, Belgium) and the <italic>Rwanda Archief</italic> of the adoption organisation <sc>vzw</sc> de Vreugdezaaiers (private archive, Gent, Belgium).</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn16">
<p>15&#x2002;16 in-depth interviews with displaced children, foster families, social workers and religious authorities were conducted between April 2010 and December 2011 in the context of the research project &#x2018;Kinderen van Save: gestolen of gered&#x2019; at <sc>cegesoma</sc>. Additionally, 17 interviews conducted by reporter Aline Wavreille in Rwanda and Burundi with non-evacuated children and the families of evacuated children were conducted in April 2011. All interviews are preserved at the archive of <sc>cegesoma</sc>, Centre for historical research and Documentation on war and contemporary society, Brussels, Belgium. Due to privacy concerns aliases are used to refer to displaced children and their parents.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn17">
<p>16&#x2002;The territory of Ruanda-Urundi was confided to Belgium as a League of Nations Mandate after Belgian and Congolese troops had successfully defeated the Germans in Tabora (German East Africa, current Tanzania) during the Great War. Later, the region was converted to a United Nations trusteeship.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn18">
<p>17&#x2002;A. Lauro, <italic>Coloniaux, m&#x00E9;nag&#x00E8;res et prostitu&#x00E9;es au Congo belge (1885&#x2013;1930)</italic> (Loverval 2005) 124&#x2013;140.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn19">
<p>18&#x2002;B. de Hart, &#x2018;"De verwerpelijkste van alle gemengde huwelijken". De gemengde Huwelijken Regeling Nederlands-Indi&#x00EB; 1898 en de rijkswet op het Nederlanderschap 1892 vergeleken&#x2019;, in: <italic>Jaarboek voor Vrouwengeschiedenis</italic> 21 (Amsterdam 2001) 60&#x2013;81.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn20">
<p>19&#x2002;Africa Archives of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs (<sc>mfa</sc>-<sc>aa</sc>), Brussels, A 61, Archives du Rwanda-Urundi d&#x2019;un caract&#x00E8;re d&#x00E9;licat.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn21">
<p>20&#x2002;S. Bushayija, <italic>Le mariage coutumier au Rwanda</italic> (Bruxelles 1966) 28&#x2013;33.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn22">
<p>21&#x2002;<sc>mfa</sc>-<sc>aa</sc>, Brussels, A 61, Archives du Rwanda-Urundi d&#x2019;un caract&#x00E8;re d&#x00E9;licat, <sc>rwabu</sc> bundle 217A, <italic>Recherche de paternit&#x00E9;.</italic> All translations by the author.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn23">
<p>22&#x2002;<sc>mfa</sc>-<sc>aa</sc>, Brussels, A 61, Archives du Rwanda-Urundi d&#x2019;un caract&#x00E8;re d&#x00E9;licat, <sc>rwabu</sc> bundle 84.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn24">
<p>23&#x2002;V. Jefremovas, &#x2018;Loose women, virtuous wives, and timid virgins: gender and the control of resources in Rwanda&#x2019;, <italic>Canadian Journal of African Studies</italic> 25:3 (1991) 378&#x2013;395, 379&#x2013;380.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn25">
<p>24&#x2002;<sc>mfa</sc>-<sc>aa</sc>, Brussels, A 61, Archives du Rwanda-Urundi d&#x2019;un caract&#x00E8;re d&#x00E9;licat, <sc>rwabu</sc> bundle 163 and bundle 33C.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn26">
<p>25&#x2002;Stoler, <italic>Carnal knowledge and imperial power</italic>, 79&#x2013;81.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn27">
<p>26&#x2002;T. De Meester, &#x2018;Nationaliteit in Belgisch Congo: constructie en verbeelding&#x2019;, <italic>Afrika Focus</italic> 14:1 (1998) 7&#x2013;16, 11&#x2013;12.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn28">
<p>27&#x2002;More about the exact nature of the problem and the specific challenges the in-between position of the biracial children posed, can be found in L. Jeurissen, &#x2018;Les ambitions du colonialisme belge pour la "race mul&#x00E2;tre" (1918&#x2013;1940)&#x2019;, <italic>Revue belge d&#x2019;histoire contemporaine</italic> 32:3&#x2013;4 (2002) 497&#x2013;535 ; L. Jeurissen, <italic>Quand le m&#x00E9;tis s&#x2019;appelait "mul&#x00E2;tre" soci&#x00E9;t&#x00E9;, droit et pouvoir coloniaux face &#x00E0; la descendance des couples eurafricains dans l&#x2019;ancien Congo Belge</italic> (Louvain-la-Neuve 2003) 120.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn29">
<p>28&#x2002;Jeurissen, <italic>Quand le m&#x00E9;tis s&#x2019;appelait &#x2018;mul&#x00E2;tre&#x2019;,</italic> 45&#x2013;50.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn30">
<p>29&#x2002;Jeurissen, <italic>Les ambitions du colonialisme belge</italic>, 526&#x2013;527. Decrees of 12 July 1890 and 3 January 1931.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn31">
<p>30&#x2002;Minist&#x00E8;re des colonies (Eds.), <italic>Recueil &#x00E0; l&#x2019;usage des fonctionnaires et des agents du Service territorial (<sc>rufast</sc>)</italic> (Bruxelles 1925) 372.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn32">
<p>31&#x2002;See articles 255, 256 and 257 of the <italic>Code Civil Congolais</italic>. Further information on the custody legislation can be found in Albert Sohier and Maurice Verstraete, <italic>Droit civil du Congo Belge, tome 1: Les personnes et la famille</italic> (Brussels 1956) art. 475.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn33">
<p>32&#x2002;Bulletin Officiel du Congo Belge (Bruxelles 1952) 2056&#x2013;2068. This decree replaced the articles 98, 264 and 266 of the first book of the Civil Code.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn34">
<p>33&#x2002;<sc>mfa</sc>-<sc>aa</sc>, Brussels, <italic>Affaires Indig&#x00E8;nes 3733</italic>, no. 219, directory "transfert enfants mul&#x00E2;tres et adoption".</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn35">
<p>34&#x2002;A. Rubbens, &#x2018;De sociale bevordering van de mulatten&#x2019;, <italic>Za&#x00EF;re</italic><sc>viii</sc>: 5 (1954) 507&#x2013;212, 508&#x2013;509; <sc>mfa</sc>-<sc>aa</sc>, Brussels<italic>, Affaires Indig&#x00E8;nes</italic>, 1417 <sc>iv</sc>-B; Jeurissen, &#x2018;Les ambitions du colonialisme belge&#x2019;, 502.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn36">
<p>35&#x2002;G. Van Der Schueren, <italic>Onze kolonie en de kolonisatie. Voordrachten en lezingen gehouden in het koloniaal universitair centrum</italic> (Antwerpen 1946) 346. All translations by the author.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn37">
<p>36&#x2002;African Archives of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Brussels, <italic>Affaires Indig&#x00E8;nes 4647</italic>, Dr. Dryepondt, la question des m&#x00E9;tis au Congo Belge. "Causerie faite au Cercle Africain &#x00E0; Bruxelles par le Dr. Dryepondt", in: <italic>Notre colonie</italic>, 13.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn38">
<p>37&#x2002;J. Pholien, &#x2018;La condition juridique et sociale des m&#x00E9;tis et des indig&#x00E8;nes&#x2019;, <italic>Extrait du Bulletin de la Soci&#x00E9;t&#x00E9; belge d&#x2019;Etudes coloniales</italic> 5 (1913) 1&#x2013;38, 4.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn39">
<p>38&#x2002;Some information about institutions where mixed-race children were instructed can be found in Jeurissen, <italic>Quand le m&#x00E9;tis s&#x2019;appelait "mul&#x00E2;tre"</italic>, 53&#x2013;56; A. Budagwa, <italic>Noirs-Blanc M&#x00E9;tis. La Belgique et la s&#x00E9;gr&#x00E9;gation des m&#x00E9;tis du Congo belge et du Ruanda-Urundi (1908&#x2013;1960</italic>) (2014) 167&#x2013;211. However, the Congo-case has not been sufficiently investigated.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn40">
<p>39&#x2002;<sc>mfa</sc>-<sc>aa</sc>, Brussels, <sc>rudi</sc>, <italic>35 (190),</italic> "Note relative aux enfants mul&#x00E2;tres de Ruanda-Urundi" of Roger de Wilde d&#x2019;Estmael to the Minister of Belgian Congo and Rwanda and Burundi, 1 January 1959.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn41">
<p>40&#x2002;Based on the combined data from the personal files held at the <sc>mfa</sc>-<sc>aa</sc> (A 61: <italic>Archives du Rwanda-Urundi d&#x2019;un caract&#x00E8;re d&#x00E9;licat</italic>), the personal files of the archive of <sc>appm</sc>, the <sc>vzw</sc> de Vreugdezaaiers (<italic>Rwanda Archief</italic>) and the <italic>Ruandafonds</italic> archive.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn42">
<p>41&#x2002;Archive of <sc>vzw</sc> de Vreugdezaaiers (<sc>vz</sc>), <italic>Rwanda Archief,</italic> Save Geschiedenis, Documen&#x00AD;tation file of Soeur Lutgardis sent to August De Schryver, minister of Belgian Congo and Ruanda-Urundi 26 October 1959, Save.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn43">
<p>42&#x2002;Interview G.R, Brussels, 11 January 2011, Sarah Heynssens, <sc>cegesoma</sc>. All translations by the author.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn44">
<p>43&#x2002;Budagwa, <italic>Noirs-Blancs, M&#x00E9;tis,</italic> 302, 314.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn45">
<p>44&#x2002;Ghequi&#x00E8;re and Kanobana, <italic>De bastaards van onze kolonie,</italic> 50. All translations by the author.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn46">
<p>45&#x2002;<sc>vz</sc>, <italic>Rwanda Archief</italic>, Save Geschiedenis, R&#x00E9;ponses aux questions pos&#x00E9;es par M. L&#x2019;abb&#x00E9; Jean Kagiranema, Save, 16 October 1957.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn47">
<p>46&#x2002;Ghequi&#x00E8;re and Kanobana, <italic>De bastaards van onze kolonie</italic>, 22&#x2013;23.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn48">
<p>47&#x2002;More detailed information about the modalities of the transfer to Belgium can be found in S. Heynssens, &#x2018;Entre deux mondes. Le d&#x00E9;placement des enfants m&#x00E9;tis du Ruanda-Urundi colonial vers la Belgique&#x2019;, <italic>Enfances d&#x00E9;plac&#x00E9;es en situation coloniale</italic> edited by Mathias Gardet and David Niget, Revue d&#x2019;Histoire de l&#x2019;enfance "irr&#x00E9;guli&#x00E8;re" 14 (2012) 97&#x2013;121.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn49">
<p>48&#x2002;Sister Lutgardis was born in 1917 as Irma de Rijcke in Moerzeke, Belgium. She became head mistress of Save in 1954 and stayed in charge of the institution until independence. She dedicated her further live and career to children: during the sixties she spent ten years in Burundi teaching. Later she worked for the &#x2018;Vreugdezaaiers&#x2019;.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn50">
<p>49&#x2002;<sc>mfa</sc>-<sc>aa</sc>, Brussels, Groupe de travail pour l&#x2019;&#x00E9;tude du probl&#x00E8;me politique au Ruanda-Urundi: comptes rendus des audiences et notes d&#x00E9;pos&#x00E9;es. Deuxi&#x00E8;me partie: Ruanda, premier fascicule, p. 1&#x2013;154. <sc>xii</sc>-3-Audition de la <sc>rsm</sc> Lutgardis, 24 April 1959, 24.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn51">
<p>50&#x2002;Interview with Sister Lutgardis, <sc>vrt</sc> Beeldarchief: Panorama <sc>brtn</sc>, 4 May 1973, reportage by William Van Laeken; interview with Sister Lutgardis, 8 June 1987 as published in Budagwa, <italic>Noirs-blancs</italic>, <italic>M&#x00E9;tis,</italic> p. 307. During the inauguration of the chapel of Save in 1957, Sister Lutgardis speaks with Mwami Mutara <sc>iii</sc>. However, today, Mwami Kigeli V, the successor of Mutara, confirms having spoken to her as well in August 1959, directly after his inauguration. It is likely she indeed spoke with both Mwami&#x2019;s as she already started lobbying for the evacuation of the children in 1958.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn52">
<p>51&#x2002;<sc>vz</sc>, <italic>Rwanda Archief</italic>, Geschiedenis Save, Letter of Sister Lutgardis to August De Schryver in his capacity of president of the Groupe de travail de Ruanda-Urundi, Astrida, 23 April 1959.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn53">
<p>52&#x2002;I. Vijgen, <italic>Tussen mandaat en kolonie. Rwanda, Burundi en het Belgische bestuur in opdracht van de Volkenbond (1916&#x2013;1932)</italic> (Leuven 2005) 131&#x2013;136. To learn more about the social revolution in Rwanda see also R. Lemarchand, <italic>Rwanda and Burundi</italic> (New York 1970) 118&#x2013;196; J.P. Chr&#x00E9;tien, <italic>The great lakes of Africa: Two thousand years of history</italic> (New York 2003); F. Reyntjens, <italic>Pouvoir et droit au Rwanda : droit public et evolution politique</italic>, 1916&#x2013;1973 (Tervuren 1985).</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn54">
<p>53&#x2002;L. Saur, &#x2018;La fronti&#x00E8;re ethnique comme outil de conqu&#x00EA;te du pouvoir: le cas du Parmehutu&#x2019;, <italic>Journal of Eastern African Studies</italic> 3:2 (2009) 303&#x2013;316, 308&#x2013;312.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn55">
<p>54&#x2002;A. al&#x2019;Amin Mazrui, <italic>The warrior tradition in modern Africa</italic> (Leiden 1977) 66; R. Lemarchand, <italic>Rwanda and Burundi</italic> (New York 1970) 166.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn56">
<p>55&#x2002;Interview G.R., 11 January 2011, Liedekerke, Sarah Heynssens, <sc>cegesoma</sc>; interview J.J., April 2011, Rwanda, Aline Wavreille, <sc>cegesoma</sc>; interview L.K., 29 October 2010, Kruishoutem, Sarah Heynssens, <sc>cegesoma</sc>; Assumani Budagwa, <italic>Noirs-blanc, m&#x00E9;tis</italic>, p. 315 (interview Maria Neys).</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn57">
<p>56&#x2002;Explanations for this high number of Tutsi metis can be found in the higher positions Tutsi occupied in society leading to more intense contact with Europeans.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn58">
<p>57&#x2002;Interview Sister Maria Andrea, 21 November 2010, Antwerp, Sarah Heynssens. A similar point of view was uttered in the documentary <italic>Bulaya, qu&#x2019; as-tu fait de mon enfant</italic>.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn59">
<p>58&#x2002;Interview G.R., 11 January 2011, Liedekerke, Sarah Heynssens, <sc>cegesoma</sc>. All translations by the author.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn60">
<p>59&#x2002;<sc>mfa</sc>-<sc>aa</sc>, <italic>Affaires Indig&#x00E8;nes 3733</italic>, no. 219, letter of Sister Lutgardis to Mr. De Schryver, Transfert enfants mul&#x00E2;tres et adoption, Save, 11 March 1960. All translations by the author.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn61">
<p>60&#x2002;<sc>mfa</sc>-<sc>aa</sc>, <italic>Affaires Indig&#x00E8;nes 3733</italic>, no. 219, directory &#x2018;transfert enfants mul&#x00E2;tres et adoption&#x2019;, Letter of J. Wertz to Minister De Schryver, Brussels, 30 July 1959.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn62">
<p>61&#x2002;<sc>mfa</sc>-<sc>aa</sc>, <italic>A 61, Archives du Ruanda-Urundi d&#x2019;un caract&#x00E8;re d&#x00E9;licat</italic>, <sc>rwabu</sc> bundle 95, Letter from the <italic>Service Affaires Indig&#x00E8;nes</italic> to the <italic>Institut pour mul&#x00E2;tres de Save</italic>, 6 March 1959.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn63">
<p>62&#x2002;<sc>mfa</sc>-<sc>aa</sc>, <italic>Affaires Indig&#x00E8;nes 3733</italic>, bundle no. 219, directory &#x2018;transfert enfants mul&#x00E2;tres et adoption&#x2019;, letter of the Ruanda Fund and P.E. Delooz to Minister De Schryver, Brussels, 1 March 1960 and 23 March 1960.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn64">
<p>63&#x2002;Heynssens, &#x2018;Entre deux mondes&#x2019;, 97&#x2013;121.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn65">
<p>64&#x2002;<sc>mfa</sc>-<sc>aa</sc>, <italic>Affaires Indig&#x00E8;nes 3733</italic>, no. 219, directory "transfert enfants mul&#x00E2;tres et adoption", letter of Sister Lutgardis to Minister De Schryver of 10 and 11 March 1960, Astrida.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn66">
<p>65&#x2002;Some smaller groups of Congolese Eurafricans were brought to Belgium by religious and charitable institutions.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn67">
<p>66&#x2002;Interview J.G, April 2011, Rwanda, Sarah Heynssens, <sc>cegesoma</sc>. All translations by the author.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn68">
<p>67&#x2002;<sc>mfa</sc>-<sc>aa</sc>, A61, Archives du Ruanda-Urundi d&#x2019;un caract&#x00E8;re d&#x00E9;licat, <sc>rwabu</sc> bundle 284, Letter of 14 April 1959.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn69">
<p>68&#x2002;Sohier and Verstraete, <italic>Droit civil du Congo Belge,</italic> 534, art. 462. (Code Civil Congolais, art. 257.)</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn70">
<p>69&#x2002;Interview M.L., April 2011, Rwanda, Sarah Heynssens, <sc>cegesoma</sc>. All translations by the author.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn71">
<p>70&#x2002;Interview M.G., April 2011, Rwanda, Sarah Heynssens, <sc>cegesoma</sc>. All translations by the author.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn72">
<p>71&#x2002;Archive of the Royal Museum for Central Africa (<sc>rmca</sc>), <italic><sc>appm</sc></italic>, letter of Paul Coppens, President of the <sc>appm</sc> to the Ruanda Fund, Brussels, 7 April 1961 and <sc>mfa</sc>-<sc>aa</sc>, A 61, Archives du Ruanda-Urundi d&#x2019;un caract&#x00E8;re d&#x00E9;licat, <sc>rwabu</sc> bundle 55.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn73">
<p>72&#x2002;Interview L.K., 29 October 2010, Kruishoutem, Sarah Heynssens, <sc>cegesoma</sc>. All translations by the author.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn74">
<p>73&#x2002;Interview J.J., April 2011, Brussels, Belgium, Sarah Heynssens, <sc>cegesoma</sc> All translations by the author.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn75">
<p>74&#x2002;<sc>mfa</sc>-<sc>aa</sc>, A61, Archives du Ruanda-Urundi d&#x2019;un caract&#x00E8;re d&#x00E9;licat, <sc>rwabu</sc> Bundle 26; 285; 286 ; 287 ; 119 ; 121 ; 106B ; 145 ; 148 ; 169 ; 169A ; 186 ; 197; 210, 213 ; 213A ; 219.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn76">
<p>75&#x2002;Interview L.K, 29 October 2010, Kruishoutem, Belgium, Sarah Heynssens, <sc>cegesoma</sc>. All translations by the author.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn77">
<p>76&#x2002;Interview M.G., April 2011, Rwanda, Aline Wavreille, <sc>cegesoma</sc>. All translations by the author.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn78">
<p>77&#x2002;<sc>vz</sc>, <italic>Rwanda Archief</italic>, individuele fiches en dossiers, letter of Miss. M.G.T. to the Reverend Sister Lutgardis Maria of the <italic>Soeurs Blanches</italic>, Bukavu, 27 February 1960. All translations by the author.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn79">
<p>78&#x2002;<sc>mfa</sc>-<sc>aa</sc>, A61, Archives du Ruanda-Urundi d&#x2019;un caract&#x00E8;re d&#x00E9;licat, <sc>rwabu</sc> bundle 220. All translations by the author.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn80">
<p>79&#x2002;<sc>mfa</sc>-<sc>aa</sc>, A61, Archives du Ruanda-Urundi d&#x2019;un caract&#x00E8;re d&#x00E9;licat, <sc>rwabu</sc> bundle 228. All translations by the author.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn81">
<p>80&#x2002;<sc>mfa</sc>-<sc>aa</sc>, A61, Archives du Ruanda-Urundi d&#x2019;un caract&#x00E8;re d&#x00E9;licat, <sc>rwabu</sc> bundle 148. All translations by the author.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn82">
<p>81&#x2002;<sc>mfa</sc>-<sc>aa</sc>, <italic>Affaires Indig&#x00E8;nes 3733</italic>, no. 219, directory "transfert enfants mul&#x00E2;tres et adoption", letter of Paul Coppens, president of the <italic>Association pour la protection des mul&#x00E2;tres</italic> (<sc>appm</sc>), to father Dury, Missionary, s.d., Brussels.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn83">
<p>82&#x2002;<sc>mfa</sc>-<sc>aa</sc>, <italic>Affaires Indig&#x00E8;nes 3733</italic>, no. 219, directory "transfert enfants mul&#x00E2;tres et adoption", Refus de maman.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn84">
<p>83&#x2002;<sc>mfa</sc>-<sc>aa</sc>, A61, Archives du Ruanda-Urundi d&#x2019;un caract&#x00E8;re d&#x00E9;licat, <sc>rwabu</sc> bundle 186. All translations by the author.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="fn85">
<p>84&#x2002;Christina Firpo and Margaret Jacobs, &#x2018;Imagined Families: colonialism, nationalism and child removals 1890&#x2013;1980&#x2019; presentation for the 16th Berkshire Conference on the History of Women, Toronto, Canada, 23 May 2014.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</back>
</article>
