<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://bookandbyte.universiteitleiden.nl/schema/tei_all.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="xxxxx">
    <!-- replace xxxxxxxxxx with file id -->
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <!-- sender --> to <!-- recipient-->, <!-- date -->: A
                    machine-readable transcription</title>
                <author>
                    <!-- sender -->
                </author>
                <principal>Prof. dr. Adriaan van der Weel</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
                    <name>
                        <!-- your name -->
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup: </resp>
                    <name>
                        <!-- your name -->
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Editorial annotations: </resp>
                    <name>
                        <!-- your name -->
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>
                <!-- file size in kBytes -->
            </extent>


            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>Leiden University</distributor>
                <pubPlace>Leiden, The Netherlands </pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 9515</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>2300 RA Leiden</addrLine>
                </address>
                <idno>
                    <!-- file ID -->
                </idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>Publicly accessible </p>
                </availability>
                <date><!-- current year --></date>
            </publicationStmt>


            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Letter from <!-- sender --> to <!-- recipient-->, <!-- date -->
                    </title>
                    <author>
                        <!-- sender -->
                    </author>
                    <idno type="callNo">
                        <!-- library callnumber -->
                    </idno>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Prepared by students of the <!-- current_academic_year_expressed as 20..-20.. -->
                    <!-- name_of_course --> course, Book and Digital Media Studies, Leiden
                    University</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p/>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="dut">Dutch</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://classificationweb.net">
                    <term>Correspondence</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://www.bookstudies.leidenuniv.nl/">
                    <term>nonfiction</term>
                    <term>prose</term>
                    <term>masculine</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <p>
                    TEI ID: Q40909_19290712.xml
                    This is a letter sent by <persName key="Q5294054">Mr.Donald C. Brace</persName>, addressed to 
                    <persName key="Q40909">Mrs.Virginia Woolf</persName>.
                    The letter concerns the publication of <persName key="Q40909">Mrs.Woolf's</persName> title <title>A Room of One's Own</title>,
                    as well as the possible publication of a limited edition. The letter includes discussions on the rights of publication
                    and the parties involved with her current title, as well as her previous title <title>Orlando</title>.
                </p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>
                            New York
                        </placeName>
                        <date when="1929-07-12">
                           July 12, 1292
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>
                            <persName key="Q40909">
                                Mrs.Virginia Woolf
                            </persName>
                        </addrLine>
                        <addrLine>
                            52 Tavistock Square
                        </addrLine>
                        <addrLine>
                            London, W.C.1
                        </addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <salute>
                        Dear <persName key="Q40909">Mrs.Woolf</persName>:
                    </salute>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    Thank you for your letter of June 30th enclosing the 
                    <lb/>signed copy of the agreement for <title>A ROOM OF ONE'S OWN</title>. I am 
                    <lb/>quite willing to have you retain the Canadian rights if you wish.
                </p>
                <p>
                    In regard to serialization, I had been doing nothing 
                    <lb/>because I thought it was your wish to abandon the idea. In 
                    <lb/><persName key="Q703935">Mr.Woolf's</persName> letter of May 16th, he said: "We will not trouble 
                    <lb/>about serialization, but go straight ahead with publication in 
                    <lb/>book form." And besides, the manuscript has been in <persName>Mr.
                    <lb/>Wells's</persName> hands. I got the manuscript back from him yesterday, 
                    <lb/>and have delivered it to <emph rend="underlined">The Bookman</emph>. I am sorry if I have 
                    <lb/>misinterpreted your wishes, but no doubt there is still time 
                    <lb/>as far as <emph rend="underlined">The Bookman</emph> is concerned.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Meanwhile, just after I received your letter, <persName>Curtis 
                    <lb/>Brown's</persName> office telephoned to ask if they could get the manuscript, 
                    <lb/>saying that they had a message from you to get in touch with 
                    <lb/>us about it. I believe <emph rend="underlined">The Bookman</emph> had already been asking 
                    <lb/><persName>Curtis Brown</persName>. If I get further inquiries from <persName>Curtis Brown</persName>, 
                    <lb/>I shall tell them that we are dealing with the matter by your
                    <lb/>instructions. Of course, if it appears that the business ought
                    <lb/>to go through <persName>Curtis Brown</persName> and they ought to have commission, 
                    <lb/>we should be glad to stand aside as far as any commission is 
                    <lb/>concerned and continue to do what we can do to dispose of the 
                    <lb/>rights.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Mr.Wells</persName> tells me that he has made you an offer in
                    <lb/>respect to a limited edition. If there is to be a limited 
                    <lb/>edition, we shall gladly co-operate with <persName>Mr.Wells</persName> and with 
                    <lb/>you in regard to arranging dates of publication and protection 
                    <lb/>of the copyright. I hope it may be possible for you to send
                    <lb/>soon finally corrected proofs, especially if there is to be a 
                    <lb/>limited edition. If you could arrange to send duplicate final 
                    <lb/>proofs so that <persName>Mr.Wells</persName> could have
                    <lb/>one set and we could have the other, matters would be greatly expedited.
                </p>
                    
                  <pb/>
                <p>
                    
                    <lb/>There is one thing about the limited edition matter 
                    <lb/>which I think I ought to mention, though I do so with some 
                    <lb/>hesitation. When I recommended the publication of a limited 
                    <lb/>edition of <title>ORLANDO</title> by <persName>Mr. Gaige</persName>, my recommendation was 
                    <lb/>based on long knowledge of him and complete certainty of his
                    <lb/>reliability. As for his successors, I have not the same 
                    <lb/>knowledge or the same certainty, and I should have hesitated 
                    <lb/>to make a similar recommendation. Of course, you are dealing 
                    <lb/>with Messrs.<persName>Wells</persName> and <unclear reason="illegible"><persName>Adams</persName></unclear> direct, and it is probably all
                    <lb/>right for you to take whatever risk is involved. It is 
                    <lb/>simply that I really know next to nothing about them, and that 
                    <lb/>in succeeding <persName>Mr.Gaige</persName>, they do not succeed to the complete
                    <lb/>confidence I have in him. Please don't take this any more 
                    <lb/>seriously than it is intended.
                </p>
                <p>
                    With kindest regards to yourself and <persName key="Q703935" >Mr.Woolf</persName>, 
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>
                        Yours sincerely,
                    </salute>
                    <signed>
                        <persName key="Q5294054">Donald C. Brace</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
    
</TEI>
