<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://bookandbyte.universiteitleiden.nl/schema/tei_all.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="xxxxx">
    <!-- replace xxxxxxxxxx with file id -->
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <!-- sender --> to <!-- recipient-->, <!-- date -->: A
                    machine-readable transcription</title>
                <author>
                    <!-- sender -->
                </author>
                <principal>Prof. dr. Adriaan van der Weel</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
                    <name>
                        <!-- your name -->
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup: </resp>
                    <name>
                        <!-- your name -->
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Editorial annotations: </resp>
                    <name>
                        <!-- your name -->
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>
                <!-- file size in kBytes -->
            </extent>


            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>Leiden University</distributor>
                <pubPlace>Leiden, The Netherlands </pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 9515</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>2300 RA Leiden</addrLine>
                </address>
                <idno>
                    <!-- file ID -->
                </idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>Publicly accessible </p>
                </availability>
                <date><!-- current year --></date>
            </publicationStmt>


            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Letter from <!-- sender --> to <!-- recipient-->, <!-- date -->
                    </title>
                    <author>
                        <!-- sender -->
                    </author>
                    <idno type="callNo">
                        <!-- library callnumber -->
                    </idno>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Prepared by students of the <!-- current_academic_year_expressed as 20..-20.. -->
                    <!-- name_of_course --> course, Book and Digital Media Studies, Leiden
                    University</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p/>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="dut">Dutch</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://classificationweb.net">
                    <term>Correspondence</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://www.bookstudies.leidenuniv.nl/">
                    <term>nonfiction</term>
                    <term>prose</term>
                    <term>masculine</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <p>
                    <!-- summary of contents -->
                </p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>
                            New York
                        </placeName>
                        <date when="1929-08-01">
                            August 1, 1929.
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>
                            <persName key="Q703935">Leonard Woolf,</persName> <choice><abbr>Esq.</abbr><expan>Esquire</expan></choice>
                        </addrLine>
                        <addrLine>52 Tavistock Square
                        </addrLine>
                        <addrLine>London, W.C.I.</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <salute>
                        Dear <persName key="Q703935">Mr. Woolf,</persName>
                    </salute>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    I have just received your letter of <date when="1929-07-23">July 23rd</date> on <lb/>
                    the subject of the limited edition of <persName key="Q40909">Mrs. Woolf</persName>’s <title>A ROOM <lb/> 
                        OF ONE’S OWN.</title> I hope my cable in reply to yours explained <lb/> my view of the
                    copyright question with reasonable clearness. <lb/> When I gave the manuscript to <persName key="MAPP0013">Mr. Wells</persName>, I 
                    explained that we <lb/> did not agree with his view of the copyright matter and that<lb/> we were making
                    a condition that the book should be printed<lb/> in this country. We had some discussion of the 
                    matter at<lb/> that time, and the next I heard about it was your cable. When<lb/> <persName key="MAPP0013">Mr. Wells</persName> says that he
                    can safeguard the copyright by depositing<lb/> two copies in Washington, he is, it seems to me,
                    rather<lb/> curiously evading the point. It is, of course, true that we<lb/> can obtain ad interim copyright 
                    for a book by a foreign author<lb/> in the English language. This is a procedure we have followed<lb/>
                    with all of <persName key="Q40909">Mrs. Woolf</persName>’s books and which we regularly follow<lb/> with all books by English authors
                    unless it turns out that we<lb/> are publishing simultaneously. But going through this formality<lb/> or
                    going through any of the formalities of copyright doesn’t mean<lb/> that the copyright is sound if it
                    is open to attack. Our view<lb/> and the view of most publishers here as far as I know is<lb/> that the
                    publication of an edition in this country from<lb/> imported sheets does invalidate the copyright
                    when such<lb/> publication is made with the consent of the author or the person<lb/> who controls the 
                    rights. The first step in obtaining<lb/> copyright in this country is publication, and the law requires<lb/>
                    that books published in this country must be printed here in<lb/> order to obtain copyright. I regard
                    the copyright as being<lb/> of more importance to you than to us, at any rate of equal<lb/> importance to
                    you. Just how important it may be, one never<lb/> knows. It is probably less important in the case 
                    of a book<lb/> like <title>A ROOM OF ONE’S OWN</title> than it would be in the case of a novel<lb/> where dramatic 
                    and picture rights might be involved as well as<lb/> book rights. The life of copyright under our law 
                    is 56 years,<lb/> and it is, of course, impossible to tell how important the<lb/> matter may turn out to be 
                    during that period. We can go<lb/> through the formalities of making copyright registration after
                 
                </p>
                <pb/>
                <p>
                    the publication of an important edition, and if no one ever<lb/> infringes no question will ever arise, 
                    but if there should<lb/> be an infringement I think our case would be a poor one because<lb/> we should 
                    come into court with the burden of having violated<lb/> certainly the spirit, if not the letter of the law 
                    ourselves.
                </p>
                <p>
                    I am sure you will understand that I am not trying to<lb/> be an obstruction in the matter. I 
                    certainly cannot advise<lb/> you that <persName key="MAPP0013">Wells</persName>’s publishing an important edition is correct from<lb/> the 
                    point of view of copyright, and also certainly he cannot<lb/> &quot; safeguard &quot; the copyright by following 
                    the procedure of<lb/> deposit and registration. At the same time I quite realize<lb/> that no question may 
                    ever arise, and I therefore told you in<lb/> my cable that we should make no objection if you feel like<lb/> 
                    taking the risk.
                     </p>
                <p>
                    I shall look forward to the corrected proofs, and we <lb/> shall plan to publish simultaneously 
                    with you on <date when="1929-11-01">November first</date><lb/> or preferably somewhat earlier if we can both get ready<lb/> in time. +
                </p>
                <p>
                    I have shown the manuscript to the Bookman, and they<lb/> have returned it with word that 
                    they find themselves unable to<lb/> use it. Their reason is that they find it impractical to pick<lb/> out one 
                    or two installments and there is no time to print the<lb/> whole. We shall see whether something can 
                    be done in another<lb/> quarter, though of course there is not much time now.
                    
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>
                        With kind regards, <lb/>
                        Yours Sincerely,
               </salute>
                    <signed>Donald Brace</signed>
                    <seg type="postscript">
                      
                       DCB:CMc <lb/>
                    
                    + Since dictating the above, I have had a talk with <persName key="MAPP0013">Mr.<lb/> Wells</persName> over the telephone. He
                            appears now to think less<lb/> highly of the idea of importing sheets from you and asks<lb/> whether we
                            might let him print the copies he might require<lb/> for America from our type. This privilege I
                            should, of course,<lb/> be entirely willing to give him, so perhaps the matter will work<lb/> out in that
                            way to the better satisfaction of everyone concerned. </seg>
                        
                    <seg type="postscript"> In regard to the date of publication, we should very<lb/> much prefer the limited edition to 
                        come out practically<lb/> simultaneously with our edition, and <persName key="MAPP0013">Mr. Wells</persName> says he would<lb/> prefer it, too. 
                        If his edition were to come out, say, 30 days<lb/> before ours, the book would get reviewed from the 
                        limited<lb/> edition in certain quarters, whereas if they are appearing at </seg>
                        
                 <pb/>
                    <seg type="postscript">about the same time, the reviews will mention both editions.<lb/> I expect you will agree with this. 
                        Immediately upon receipt<lb/> of the corrected proofs, we shall go ahead with all possible<lb/> speed, 
                        and if <persName key="MAPP0013">Mr. Wells</persName> has fixed up with you and wants to<lb/> use our type, we will release it to him as 
                        early as we can.</seg> 
                    
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
