<xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8">
<DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/2.3/journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="e-issn">1871191X</journal-id>
<journal-title>The Hague Journal of Diplomacy</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>HJD</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1871-1901</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1871-191X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Brill | Nijhoff</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>The Netherlands</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1163/1871191X-13020004</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Strategic Publics in Public Diplomacy: A Typology and a Heuristic Device for Multiple Publics</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pacher</surname>
<given-names>Andreas</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn0">*</xref>
<aff>
<institution>Nouvelle Europe</institution>
<addr-line>1120 Vienna</addr-line>
<country>Austria</country>
<email>andreas.pacher@sciencespo.fr</email>
</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="corresp" id="fn0">
<p>* The author extends his special thanks to Pierre H.N. Martin. He is also indebted to Manon Bellon, Svetlana Kim, Liu Yongtao, and Sun Fanglu, as well as to two anonymous reviewers, for their excellent and critical comments.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>7</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>13</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>272</fpage>
<lpage>296</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<month>2 February</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<month>27 May</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<month>27 June</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>&#x00A9; Koninklijke Brill NV, Leiden, The Netherlands</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Koninklijke Brill NV, Leiden, The Netherlands</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<self-uri xlink:href="1871191X_013_03_s002_text.pdf" content-type="pdf"/>
<abstract>
<p>How do governments select their public diplomacy targets? Officials can shake hands
with important allies&#x2019; presidents, they can honour writers from far-away states, or they can visit slums to meet victims of violence. This article proposes a conceptual typology of strategic publics based on two dimensions: the strategic importance of the represented polity; and the individual&#x2019;s power position. The variables are parallel to universal psychological dimensions of social cognition &#x2014; that is, warmth and competence &#x2014; and they are combined with diplomatic theories revolving around the primacy of representation. Six ideal types of strategic publics are defined and exemplified. The typology integrates governmental and non-governmental, foreign and domestic, and elite and non-elite publics. In addition, the article proposes a three-level heuristic device that facilitates the analysis of cases with multiple publics. The proposed analytical tools seek to stimulate future efforts to refine conceptualizations of strategic publics.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>public diplomacy</kwd>
<kwd>strategic publics</kwd>
<kwd>segmentation</kwd>
<kwd>targets</kwd>
<kwd>warmth and competence</kwd>
<kwd>typology</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<custom-meta-wrap>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>version</meta-name>
<meta-value>fulltext</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-wrap>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="B10.1163_1871191X-13020004_001" sec-type="head1">
<title><bold>Introduction</bold></title>
<p>If there is one sentence that embodies an utter contrast to public diplomacy, it would be the pianist Sviatoslav Richter&#x2019;s &#x2018;I don&#x2019;t play for the audience; I play for myself&#x2019;. For public diplomacy is inherently thrusted towards <italic>publics</italic>. Kathy R. Fitzpatrick termed the targets of public diplomacy &#x2018;strategic publics&#x2019;.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref> This article defines them as individuals, or groups of individuals, with whom a public diplomat establishes and maintains a relationship.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>2</sup></xref> The purpose of this article is to develop a conceptual typology of strategic publics. It does so by drawing upon psychologically universal dimensions of social cognition, and by combining them with theories that posit <italic>representation</italic> as the core essence of diplomacy. As a result, and in contrast to Sviatoslav Richter, the public diplomat playing the piano is very much concerned with the audience. The public diplomat, however, is not primarily concerned with the concrete individuals sitting in the audience hall, but rather with the polities that they represent.</p>
<p>The theory and practice of public diplomacy exhibit three unresolved issues regarding strategic publics. The first pertains to the domestic&#x2013;foreign frontier and often leaves domestic publics out of the public diplomat&#x2019;s scope. The second finds boundaries between governmental and non-state actors, and dismisses public interactions with (foreign) officials into the realm of traditional diplomacy. The third issue relates to the overemphasis on <italic>elite</italic> actors as strategic publics. However, there are neither precise boundaries between the foreign and the domestic, nor is there a clear conceptual separation of the public from the private. In addition, empirical cases and imagined scenarios allow enough room for non-elite participants of public diplomacy.</p>
<p>This article proposes a typology of strategic publics that integrates both foreign <italic>and</italic> domestic, both governmental <italic>and</italic> non-state, both powerful <italic>and</italic> powerless strategic publics. The typology is based on two dimensions: first, the represented polity&#x2019;s strategic importance in light of the public diplomat&#x2019;s objectives; and second, the individual&#x2019;s perceived power position within the represented polity. These two explanatory variables are underpinned by theories of diplomatic studies revolving around representation. They are variants of the two traits that psychologists have identified as universal elements of social cognition in both interpersonal and inter-group relations: warmth; and competence. The typology portrays six ideal types: (1) traditional diplomatic partners; (2) imminent; (3) protocollary; (4) salient; and (5) remote strategic publics; as well as (6) global mass publics. Moreover, to develop this typology further, the article proposes a basic heuristic device for analysing cases with multiple strategic publics.</p>
<p>This article&#x2019;s significance lies in expanding the scope of potential strategic publics &#x2018;to discover missed combinations and suppressed assumptions&#x2019;.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3"><sup>3</sup></xref> As with typologies and heuristic devices in general, it seeks to refresh the foundation on which hypotheses are formulated, and hopes to stimulate empirical research and offer guidance towards more refined concepts, so as to find distinct predictions associated with each type of strategic public.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4"><sup>4</sup></xref></p>
<p>The following will review the relevant literature on diplomatic theory, on segmentation of publics, on psychological aspects of social cognition and on public diplomacy. After a problem statement and a summary of the underlying theory, the article develops the typology by describing two dimensions and six ideal types, which are illustrated with examples. The subsequent section proposes a heuristic device that helps to explore the relational ties enacted with multiple publics. The final section discusses how the typology can guide us towards new research and offers conclusions.</p>
<p>The article will repeatedly use statist terminology, which is partly because of the state-centric reflections of the diplomatic theory utilized. However, the notions may analogously be applied to non-state actors.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_1871191X-13020004_002" sec-type="head1">
<title><bold>Review and Underlying Theory</bold></title>
<sec id="B10.1163_1871191X-13020004_003" sec-type="head2">
<title><bold><italic>Diplomacy as Representation</italic></bold></title>
<p>The diplomat is a &#x2018;stranger&#x2019; &#x2014; that is, an individual whose &#x2018;most obvious [characteristic] is that of belonging to another country&#x2019;.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5"><sup>5</sup></xref> Diplomats are individuals who represent abstract polities.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6"><sup>6</sup></xref> This representation forms the core essence of diplomacy.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7"><sup>7</sup></xref></p>
<p>Not only diplomats represent. In public diplomacy, participants include individuals who are not professional or accredited diplomats. Yet if diplomacy is always the mediation of mutually estranged actors,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8"><sup>8</sup></xref> and if, in all diplomacy, actors are &#x2018;experienced through their representation&#x2019;,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9"><sup>9</sup></xref> then public diplomats also regard their targeted strategic publics as representations.</p>
<p>A conceptual understanding of diplomacy prioritizes the represented entity, which renders the concrete individuals as secondary. The primary agents are the abstract polities represented by individuals. Inter-state relations are &#x2018;relations between persons, personified countries&#x2019;,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10"><sup>10</sup></xref> personified in diplomats who are the &#x2018;psychological agent[s] of the state&#x2019;.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11"><sup>11</sup></xref> For example, a negotiation between Metternich and Talleyrand was, in essence, a negotiation between Austria and France.</p>
<p>What is most fundamental in diplomacy is the representation of &#x2018;otherness&#x2019;. Diplomacy is always &#x2018;a process of Othering&#x2019;,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12"><sup>12</sup></xref> and a &#x2018;mediation to reconcile relations among states mutually estranged&#x2019;.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13"><sup>13</sup></xref> Both the public diplomat and the strategic publics are &#x2018;the embodiment[s], and for that matter the formal representative[s], of the &#x201C;other&#x201D;&#x200A;&#x2019;.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14"><sup>14</sup></xref></p>
<p>If the substance of the represented polities is this otherness, then its additional qualities are merely accidental. The debates about whether strategic publics must be &#x2018;foreign&#x2019; or whether they may also contain &#x2018;domestic&#x2019; parts are therefore misleading;<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15"><sup>15</sup></xref> and it is also misleading to retain governmental partners in the traditional diplomatic area by alleging that only non-state targets constitute real strategic publics of public diplomacy. As Bruce Gregory stresses, the thrust towards publics has always been an inseparable &#x2018;core ingredient&#x2019; of (even traditional) diplomacy.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16"><sup>16</sup></xref> In addition, an accumulating body of research in international relations and diplomatic history &#x2018;demonstrates the dividing line between state and non-state identities to be a fiction&#x2019;.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17"><sup>17</sup></xref> It has long been acknowledged that such boundaries cannot be mapped with sufficient precision, and that they remain porously opaque. If, in diplomacy, everybody represents, and if the represented entities are always Others then it is misleading to attribute accidental qualities of &#x2018;foreign&#x2019; or &#x2018;domestic&#x2019;, of &#x2018;private&#x2019; or &#x2018;public&#x2019; upon homogenously estranged Others.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_1871191X-13020004_004" sec-type="head2">
<title><bold><italic>Segmentation of Publics</italic></bold></title>
<p>Segmenting Others into various components is often performed in response to questions such as: &#x2018;In relations between human collectives, who is to be represented, why and how?&#x2019;;<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18"><sup>18</sup></xref> or &#x2018;on what basis should the sub-set of citizens to be consulted on any given issue [&#x2026;] be selected?&#x2019;<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19"><sup>19</sup></xref> The questions formulated as such ask for normative standards of selecting publics, rather than for analytical devices for descriptive purposes. The following will review some of the normative means that have been proposed in the public relations and management literature, and summarizes a descriptive psychological account of how human beings detect Others.</p>
<p>Segmentation means &#x2018;divid[ing] a population, market, or audience into groups whose members are more like each other than members of other segments&#x2019;.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20"><sup>20</sup></xref> Segmenting the environment into components of individuals or groups of individuals who affect a focal agent is an important part of the research on public relations (&#x2018;publics&#x2019;) and management (&#x2018;stakeholders&#x2019;). Without proper segmentation, one risks an &#x2018;undifferentiated communication with a general population&#x2019;, which &#x2018;is costly and ineffective&#x2019;.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21"><sup>21</sup></xref></p>
<p>Since public relations and management are sub-branches of interpersonal relations, one may dig even deeper to find how people generally perceive and classify Others. Two psychological dimensions that resulted from evolutionary pressures operate in all interhuman cognitive identifications of Others: &#x2018;In encounters with conspecifics, social animals must determine, immediately, whether the &#x201C;other&#x201D; is friend or foe (i.e. intends good or ill) and, then, whether the &#x201C;other&#x201D; has the ability to enact those intentions&#x2019;.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22"><sup>22</sup></xref> These two dimensions &#x2014; dubbed warmth and competence &#x2014; shape all intuitive and rational judgements about Others. Warmth refers to traits that disclose whether the Other&#x2019;s perceived intent is threatening to us &#x2014; such as friendliness, sincerity and trustworthiness. Competence captures traits that disclose whether the Others is capable of realizing their (threatening or kind, hostile or warm) intentions &#x2014; such as intelligence, skill and creativity. Our brain evaluates warmth within particles of a second, while the individual&#x2019;s competence needs longer time to be assessed; this is called the primacy of warmth. A large body of psychological research reached the consensus that the two dimensions of warmth and competence almost &#x2018;entirely account for how people characterize others&#x2019;<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23"><sup>23</sup></xref> in both interpersonal and intergroup settings.</p>
<p>These two dimensions co-vibrate in segmentation approaches of public relations and stakeholder theory. Stakeholders have been defined as &#x2018;any group or individual who can affect or is affected by the achievement of the firm&#x2019;s objectives&#x2019;.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24"><sup>24</sup></xref> A review of 27 stakeholder conceptualizations discovered that the two dimensions that always recur in stakeholder identifications are legitimacy and power.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25"><sup>25</sup></xref> Legitimacy is understood as &#x2018;socially accepted and expected behaviors&#x2019;, whereas power &#x2018;refers to the ability to control resources&#x2019;.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26"><sup>26</sup></xref></p>
<p>Another prominent means to segment an organization&#x2019;s environment stems from the public relations literature&#x2019;s situational theory of publics.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27"><sup>27</sup></xref> This supposes that publics &#x2014; defined as &#x2018;those who constrain or enhance an organization&#x2019;s ability to reach its goals&#x2019;<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28"><sup>28</sup></xref> &#x2014; can be classified by measuring their involvement in an issue or problem on the one hand, and their problem recognition and constraint recognition on the other hand. Involvement denotes the degree to which a problem has a bearing on a given individual; problem recognition refers to the individual&#x2019;s ability to detect issues that affect them; and constraint recognition relates to the individual&#x2019;s perception of their inability to respond effectively to the problem. In another variation, Kirk Hallahan termed the categorical variables &#x2018;involvement&#x2019; and &#x2018;knowledge&#x2019;.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29"><sup>29</sup></xref></p>
<p>The elements of legitimacy in stakeholder theory and of involvement in situational theory are both reminiscent of the universal warmth-dimension in cognitive psychology. Ultimately, what these judgements seek to fathom is whether the Others is to be feared or not &#x2014; whether one needs to be more cautious towards the Others. On the other hand, the elements of power in stakeholder theory and of recognition or knowledge in situational theory resemble the universal competence-dimension of cognitive psychology. Ultimately, what they apprehend is whether the Others possesses sufficient resources to realize its intentions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_1871191X-13020004_005" sec-type="head2">
<title><bold><italic>Strategic Publics in Public Diplomacy</italic></bold></title>
<p>The public diplomacy literature has not often explicitly dealt with strategies of identifying potential addressees. One guidance was proposed by Alison van Rooy, who formulated a system of questions that move along the two categories of legitimacy and capacity. The questions are designed to help the public diplomat in assessing the appropriateness of engaging with the potential targets (legitimacy), as well as the skills and resources that the targets have at their disposal (capacity).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30"><sup>30</sup></xref></p>
<p>In most other public diplomacy works, one can infer tacit bi-dimensional approaches in conceptualizations of strategic publics. This binary assumption is implicit in definitions of public diplomacy. For example, public diplomacy has been described as &#x2018;a government&#x2019;s process of communication with foreign publics&#x2019;,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn31"><sup>31</sup></xref> or as strategic political communication designed to &#x2018;influence public or elite opinion in a second nation&#x2019;.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn32"><sup>32</sup></xref> One can disaggregate the addressees into two conceptually distinct parts: one that designates an aggregate political community &#x2014; &#x2018;foreign&#x2019; or &#x2018;a second nation&#x2019;; and one that focuses on (groups of) individuals &#x2014; &#x2018;publics&#x2019; or &#x2018;elite&#x2019;. The former is more abstract and the latter is more concrete, but they are interlinked because the concrete represents the abstract. If diplomacy is essentially about representation,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn33"><sup>33</sup></xref> then it is the &#x2018;foreign&#x2019; part &#x2014; the represented entity &#x2014; that first and foremost constitutes the strategic publics.</p>
<p>Geoffrey Cowan and Amelia Arsenault imply that strategic publics are to be understood in terms of &#x2018;culture&#x2019; and &#x2018;individuals&#x2019;: &#x2018;While dialogue between cultures is an admirable goal, it begins with dialogue between individuals&#x2019;.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn34"><sup>34</sup></xref> The following question paraphrases this concept: Which &#x2018;individuals&#x2019; (concrete) from which &#x2018;culture&#x2019; (abstract)? In another example, Jarim Kim states that public diplomacy ought to target &#x2018;citizens in other societies&#x2019;.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn35"><sup>35</sup></xref> This can be transformed into the question: Which &#x2018;citizens&#x2019; (concrete individuals) from which &#x2018;societies&#x2019; (aggregate political entity)? And definitions operating with &#x2018;foreign publics&#x2019; can be addressed by the question: Which &#x2018;publics&#x2019; (concrete individuals) from which &#x2018;foreign&#x2019; places (abstract entity)?</p>
<p>While Alison van Rooy&#x2019;s legitimacy and capacity dimensions are immediately evocative of the warmth and competence dimensions of social psychology, the represented abstract entity (&#x2018;foreign&#x2019;, &#x2018;another society&#x2019;) and the concretized individuals who represent them (&#x2018;publics&#x2019;, &#x2018;citizens&#x2019;) are not so straightforwardly reflective of those universal psychological principles. However, Sasson Sofer&#x2019;s reflections on diplomatic otherness provide a hint:</p>
<disp-quote>
<p>Of the many characteristics attributed to the stranger, the most obvious is that of belonging to another country [&#x2026;]. The stranger is a source, sometimes, of attraction, as someone representing the &#x2018;other world&#x2019;. This attraction usually carries with it a sense of danger and doubtful loyalty. Nonetheless, there is a belief that the stranger is capable of mediating between &#x2018;this world&#x2019; and the other.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn36"><sup>36</sup></xref></p>
</disp-quote>
<p>The personified &#x2018;other world&#x2019; induces an uneasy feeling of apprehension. Facing the stranger, one is prompted to fathom whether the encounter with this Others warrants caution. This is the very same pressure that fundamentally underlies the intuitive judgement contained in the warmth-dimension in psychology. Yet despite the eerie representation, one is yet to gauge whether the concrete individual who embodies the otherness is still &#x2018;capable of mediating&#x2019;. This latter evaluation is akin to the interrogation of whether the Others is in possession of resources that are favourable to the objectives that the diplomat harbours in the back of his or her mind. In fundamental terms, it enquires into the competence of the Others and as such it is evocative of the second dimension of social cognition. The universal dimensions of warmth and competence are thus implicitly enclosed in the very definition of strategic publics as &#x2018;foreign publics&#x2019;.</p>
<p>Warmth and competence are continua: there is greater or lesser warmth; greater or lesser competence. It is self-evident that negative judgements can assess Others as cold or incompetent. However, both public diplomacy practice and theory often follow an understanding of strategic publics that excludes &#x2018;cold&#x2019; and &#x2018;incompetent&#x2019; Others. The &#x2018;willing receivers and interpreters&#x2019;<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn37"><sup>37</sup></xref> of public diplomacy are, more often than not, not only willing, but also relatively powerful. As James Pamment discovered in his research on official public diplomacy practices, the British government seeks out &#x2018;key influencers&#x2019;,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn38"><sup>38</sup></xref> <sc>US</sc>-led public diplomacy participants are likewise &#x2018;considered &#x2018;influencers&#x2019; rather than representatives of the population as a whole&#x2019;,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn39"><sup>39</sup></xref> and the Swedish government&#x2019;s understanding of public diplomacy seeks to target only those who are capable of supporting the achievement of Swedish national interests.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn40"><sup>40</sup></xref> Governments thus engage solely those &#x2018;citizens whose opinions, values, activities and interests may help sway another government&#x2019;s position&#x2019;,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn41"><sup>41</sup></xref> an approach that overemphasizes elite actors from strategically imminent polities.</p>
<p>Case studies point towards the same direction. The United States&#x2013;China Internet Industry Forum consists exclusively of important <sc>CEO</sc>s and influential elites from academia.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn42"><sup>42</sup></xref> French participants who received grants from the <sc>US</sc> State Department&#x2019;s International Visitor Leadership Program (<sc>IVLP</sc>) in 1985 came from the French civil service, academia, business and finance, politics, trade unions and journalism.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn43"><sup>43</sup></xref> Public diplomats engage famous celebrities to exploit their popularity.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn44"><sup>44</sup></xref> Educational exchange programmes are enacted only with countries that are of high bilateral strategic importance.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn45"><sup>45</sup></xref> Recipients of state awards are those who occupy positions of high authority or who are in possession of rich resources.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn46"><sup>46</sup></xref> If strategic publics are not &#x2018;current and potential opinion leaders&#x2019;,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn47"><sup>47</sup></xref> then they equal mass publics to whom public diplomats send one-way signals. Such practices place peripherical societies on &#x2018;the receiving end of <sc>PD</sc> [public diplomacy]&#x2019;,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn48"><sup>48</sup></xref> and they are evocative of Robert M. Entman&#x2019;s suggestion that public diplomacy does not seek to shape public opinion, but elite opinion.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn49"><sup>49</sup></xref></p>
<p>Only rarely do strategic publics come from weaker segments. When <sc>US</sc> President Lyndon Johnson spontaneously invited the Pakistani camel herder Bashir Ahmad to come with him to the United States, he was unexpectedly compelled to grant Ahmad a tour and to ostentatiously offer his guest various privileges during the trip. Yet that was more an accident rather than an outcome of a deliberate public diplomacy strategy.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn50"><sup>50</sup></xref> Imagined scenarios<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn51"><sup>51</sup></xref> could easily think of other settings in which public diplomats reach out to weak individuals or to representatives from strategically unimportant countries. Such strategic publics could include prisoners of war, refugees, or the impoverished. However, the targets that are taken into account by official strategies mainly consist of current or future key influencers, powerful elites and opinion leaders, or of undifferentiated mass publics who serve as anonymous multipliers of power. Kathy R. Fitzpatrick cites Jim Murphy:</p>
<disp-quote>
<p>Now the range of stakeholders on the important issues of the day can be huge &#x2014; inhabiting every corner of a country &#x2014; not just the corridors of power, but the slums, the business districts and the suburbs. And it&#x2019;s much more difficult to work out who among them are our key partners.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn52"><sup>52</sup></xref></p>
</disp-quote>
<p>As was alluded to above, the understanding of strategic publics is not only often confined to &#x2018;warm&#x2019; and &#x2018;competent&#x2019;, but also further narrowed down to &#x2018;foreign&#x2019; and &#x2018;non-state&#x2019; Others. In yet unresolved controversies, those left out are the &#x2018;not-so-warm&#x2019; and &#x2018;not-so-competent&#x2019;, as well as the &#x2018;domestic&#x2019; and the &#x2018;state&#x2019; actors. All of them, however, at least in imagination but also in some empirical cases, have the potential to be placed into public diplomacy settings. A conceptual typology must be based on variables that expand the current dimensions so as to &#x2018;identif[y] underexploited combinations&#x2019;.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn53"><sup>53</sup></xref></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_1871191X-13020004_006" sec-type="head1">
<title><bold>Problem Statement</bold></title>
<p>Practice and scholarship of public diplomacy have provided normative statements on how to select the &#x2018;right&#x2019; strategic publics. Many of them overemphasize the engagement of (potential) elite actors, which risks neglecting other segments of the population. However, rare cases and imagined scenarios demonstrate that weaker publics <italic>can</italic> be participants of public diplomacy activities, too. In addition to the almost exclusive attention on elite publics, public diplomacy literature has repeatedly debated on whether domestic constituencies and state actors can be integrated.</p>
<p>An analytical device that helps to conceptually capture the strategic publics as holistically as possible should utilize explanatory variables that enable the integration of domestic constituencies, state actors, and weaker or remote segments of the population. So far, no such typology exists that could represent all (and not merely the higher) degrees of legitimacy and power.</p>
<p>Rather than asking the normative question of &#x2018;who is to be represented?&#x2019;, it is more apt for a descriptive typology to be guided by the question of who <italic>can</italic> be represented? Such guidance helps to highlight overlooked segments, so as to enable new scenarios and partly to realize the desideratum that &#x2018;the scope of the audience for public diplomacy needs to be broadened&#x2019;.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn54"><sup>54</sup></xref></p>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_1871191X-13020004_007" sec-type="head1">
<title><bold>A Typology of Strategic Publics</bold></title>
<sec id="B10.1163_1871191X-13020004_008" sec-type="head2">
<title><bold><italic>Approach</italic></bold></title>
<p>Both public diplomats and strategic publics are concrete individuals, but are also representatives of abstract political entities. What primarily counts is the represented entity; the individual actor is secondary. The represented entity is substantively an estranged Others.</p>
<p>Since diplomacy is simply a &#x2018;distinct branch of human relations&#x2019;,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn55"><sup>55</sup></xref> the abstract political entity and the individual who represents it are captured by dimensions akin to the universal psychological aspects of social cognition &#x2014; namely, warmth and competence.</p>
<p>A dimension analogous to warmth fathoms whether the strategic public merits attention. In psychology, warmth has primacy, and so does the abstract polity in diplomacy. Therefore, a parallel dimension can be operationalized as <italic>the abstract entity&#x2019;s strategic importance in light of the public diplomat&#x2019;s foreign policy</italic> goals. The analogous competence dimension, on the other hand, seeks to evaluate the <italic>concrete individual&#x2019;s perceived power position within the represented entity</italic>. The dimensions are not dichotomously coded (presence and absence of warmth or competence), but are continua that allow assignments of greater or lesser degrees.</p>
<p>The typology posits that the two dimensions &#x2014; that is, the abstract entity&#x2019;s strategic importance and the concrete individual&#x2019;s perceived power position &#x2014; are contingent on the contextual needs of the public diplomat&#x2019;s foreign policy objectives. This underpinning derives from the fact that public diplomacy is part of diplomacy, and diplomacy, in turn, is a tool of foreign policy.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn56"><sup>56</sup></xref> Measurements and parameters vary on a case-by-case basis and must be explored by the analyst in light of the public diplomacy programme&#x2019;s objectives. Thus, the conceptual typology describes outcomes of foreign policy strategies that are to be explored.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_1871191X-13020004_009" sec-type="head2">
<title><bold><italic>The First Dimension: The Abstract Entity&#x2019;s Strategic Importance</italic></bold></title>
<sec id="B10.1163_1871191X-13020004_010" sec-type="head3">
<title>Explanation</title>
<p>Warmth, as the primary psychological dimension of evaluating Others in social cognition, seeks to evaluate the degree of threat that the Others poses. It fathoms whether the Others merits attention, and thus gauges &#x2018;perceived [good or ill] intent, friendliness, helpfulness, sincerity, [and] trustworthiness&#x2019;.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn57"><sup>57</sup></xref> It is therefore similar to the concept of involvement in public relations and to the concept of legitimacy in stakeholder theory, because higher degrees of involvement or legitimacy induce the organization to pay more attention to the public or stakeholder.</p>
<p>In public diplomacy, the analogous dimension measures the appropriateness or legitimacy of interaction with the abstract entity represented by the strategic public. The strategic public&#x2019;s legitimacy is higher when estrangement is lower; in opposite terms, legitimacy is higher when the target&#x2019;s strategic proximity to the public diplomat is higher. This dimension therefore measures the <italic>strategic public&#x2019;s strategic importance to the public diplomat&#x2019;s foreign policy goals</italic>. What counts is the degree of bilateral proximity between the two entities represented &#x2014; that is, the density of linkages between the two abstract political groupings, embodied by the public diplomat on the one hand and the strategic public on the other hand.</p>
<p>The represented abstract entity can be a state, or it can be an international organization, a multinational enterprise, a non-governmental organization, a diaspora, or any other politically relevant collective.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_1871191X-13020004_011" sec-type="head3">
<title>Measurement and Parameters</title>
<p>The mode for measuring strategic importance is context-specific, and is contingent on the public diplomat&#x2019;s perception and foreign policy goals. Parameters vary on a case-by-case basis and will likely include determinants of bilateral state relations, such as geographical proximity, density of trade and economic linkages, joint membership in international organizations, or formal status as allies or warring parties.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_1871191X-13020004_012" sec-type="head3">
<title>End-points and Middle Point</title>
<p>This dimension is a continuum with two end-points. At one end-point, the greatest strategic importance is given when the abstract entity has the densest bilateral linkages with the public diplomat (for example, a neighbouring country, the largest investor, or a powerful diaspora). The other end-point is occupied by the political entity with the least-developed or non-existent relationship. Since the dimension captures represented entities, there is another possibility for the weakest end-point: the total absence of representation. Thus, a strategic public that, from the viewpoint of the public diplomat, does not represent any political entity (for example, celebrity diplomacy) is also located at the weakest end-point.</p>
<p>The middle point of this dimension can be exemplified in the diplomatic corps or in the &#x2018;international community&#x2019; <italic>in toto</italic> because it comprises all states, regardless of whether they are strategically important or unimportant in light of the public diplomat&#x2019;s foreign policy goals.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_1871191X-13020004_013" sec-type="head2">
<title><bold><italic>The Second Dimension: The Individual&#x2019;s Perceived Power Position</italic></bold></title>
<sec id="B10.1163_1871191X-13020004_014" sec-type="head3">
<title>Explanation</title>
<p>After having identified the political entity with which the public diplomat enacts relations, the next logical step is to find apt individuals, or groups of individuals, affiliated with the political entities under consideration. The typology&#x2019;s second dimension thus moves from the abstract level of political units towards individualized persons.</p>
<p>Here, the public diplomat&#x2019;s assessment resembles the psychological competence-dimension, which parallels the knowledge- or recognition- dimension in public relations and the power-dimension in stakeholder theory. They all plumb whether the focal individual possesses the capacity to realize the public diplomat&#x2019;s intentions. The dimension thus assigns perceived power or authority to the individuals within the polity that they represent.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_1871191X-13020004_015" sec-type="head3">
<title>Measurement and Parameters</title>
<p>The selection of individuals is judged in light of foreign policy goals. The explanatory rationales underlying this dimension are, again, context-specific and contingent on the public diplomat&#x2019;s perception. In many cases, public diplomats select individuals as their strategic publics by asking the question: Who, among the represented political entity, possesses the resources that can be mobilized towards achieving my foreign policy goals? Parameters to measure the individuals&#x2019; perceived power position vary with each case. For example, &#x2018;Fulbright scholarships are awarded through a peer review process that selects scholars on the basis of academic merit&#x2019;, while &#x2018;[a]rtistic quality is a key consideration in cultural exchanges&#x2019;.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn58"><sup>58</sup></xref> More generally, parameters can be operationalized in terms of formal status of authority (for example, accreditation), resource dependency,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn59"><sup>59</sup></xref> social capital,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn60"><sup>60</sup></xref> opinion leadership,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn61"><sup>61</sup></xref> or network centrality.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn62"><sup>62</sup></xref></p>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_1871191X-13020004_016" sec-type="head3">
<title>End-points and Middle Point</title>
<p>The strongest end-point of this dimension includes traditional diplomatic and governmental actors such as heads of states and their accredited diplomats. The weakest end-point comes close to an absence of competence, and is constituted by individuals deprived of any status and rights. The middle point constitutes an undifferentiated general public that denotes a holistic mass entity, similar to the &#x2018;public&#x2019; of &#x2018;public opinion&#x2019;. Between the extreme ends of a proto-typical head of state (strongest competence) versus the powerless (weakest competence), the continuum could harbour secretary-generals of important international organizations, influential politicians, major investors, diasporic entrepreneurs, well-connected journalists, wealthy philanthropists, prominent academics, artists, writers, students, a low-level local employee in one of the public diplomat&#x2019;s consulates, or even more powerless positions, such as low-wage labourers, minorities deprived of any rights, refugees, prisoners of war, etc.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_1871191X-13020004_017" sec-type="head1">
<title><bold>The Ideal Types</bold></title>
<p>Fig. 1 illustrates the typology. Together, the two dimensions map out four quadrants, each of which denotes an ideal type. The centre of the two axes is conceptualized as global mass publics. The strongest values on the x-axis comprise traditional diplomatic actors.</p>
<fig id="f1-303272">
<label><sc>FIGURE 1</sc></label>
<caption>
<title><italic>An illustration of the typology of strategic publics</italic>.</title>
</caption>
<graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="1871191X_013_03_s002_i0001.jpg" alt-version="yes"/>
</fig>
<sec id="B10.1163_1871191X-13020004_018" sec-type="head2">
<title><bold><italic>Traditional Diplomatic Partners</italic></bold></title>
<p>The individuals with strongest perceived power (that is, the strongest values on the x-axis) are high-level state representatives such as heads of state, ministers and accredited diplomats. Combined with the y-axis, it creates a cell box that denotes traditional inter-state diplomacy, where, for instance, traditional rules of inter-state relations such as the Vienna Convention on the Law of Diplomats apply.</p>
<p>A high-level state visit is an act of public diplomacy.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn63"><sup>63</sup></xref> The host country&#x2019;s head of state can be conceptualized as the public diplomat who welcomes the strategic public, as individualized in the visiting head of state (or vice versa, depending on the units of analysis). In a specific example, President of South Korea Park Geun-hye bestowed the Grand Order of Mugunghwa &#x2014; South Korea&#x2019;s highest-ranked award &#x2014; on Indonesia&#x2019;s head of state, President Susilo Bambang Yudhoyono, in 2014.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn64"><sup>64</sup></xref></p>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_1871191X-13020004_019" sec-type="head2">
<title><bold><italic>Imminent Strategic Publics</italic></bold></title>
<p>Imminent strategic publics refer to powerful individuals (or groups of individuals) who represent strategically important political entities.</p>
<p>Examples from the literature include the annual <sc>US</sc>&#x2013;China Internet Industry Forum, where attendees are comprised of high-level, influential personalities involved in the information technology sector,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn65"><sup>65</sup></xref> and the (then) young and promising politician Nicolas Sarkozy&#x2019;s visit to the United States in 1985 within the <sc>IVLP</sc>.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn66"><sup>66</sup></xref> Another example is Russian President Vladimir Putin&#x2019;s conferral of the Order of Friendship in 2013 upon the <sc>CEO</sc> of a foreign energy company that had large investments in the Russian energy sector &#x2014; Rex Tillerson, then <sc>CEO</sc> of ExxonMobil.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn67"><sup>67</sup></xref></p>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_1871191X-13020004_020" sec-type="head2">
<title><bold><italic>Protocollary Strategic Publics</italic></bold></title>
<p>Protocollary strategic publics refer to powerful, high-authority individuals (or groups of individuals) who represent entities of low strategic importance from the public diplomat&#x2019;s viewpoint, or who lack any affiliation to a political entity.</p>
<p>One example from the literature is former British Foreign Secretary William Hague&#x2019;s utilization of &#x2018;celebrity diplomacy&#x2019;, when he co-opted film star Angelina Jolie for the &#x2018;Campaign to End Sexual Violence in Conflict&#x2019;.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn68"><sup>68</sup></xref> For this programme, Angelina Jolie&#x2019;s affiliation to an abstract political entity &#x2014; such as her American citizenship &#x2014; was irrelevant. She therefore did not represent a collective political entity, but simply herself.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn69"><sup>69</sup></xref> From the public diplomat&#x2019;s viewpoint (that is, Hague&#x2019;s), Angelina Jolie was a &#x2018;powerful&#x2019; individual because her role was to attract global attention from other potential participants. As James Pamment&#x2019;s case study shows, Jolie did indeed deliver by obtaining more views for her campaign-related postings on social media than Hague did. However, while her perceived power position was, at least in this specific campaign&#x2019;s context, rather high, Angelina Jolie exemplifies not an imminent, but a protocollary strategic public because of her absence in any polity-representation.</p>
<p>Visits of governmental officials to countries with which almost no bilateral ties exist, and where they <italic>pro forma</italic> shake hands with their counterparts, also fall under this category.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_1871191X-13020004_021" sec-type="head2">
<title><bold><italic>Salient Strategic Publics</italic></bold></title>
<p>Salient strategic publics refer to individuals (or groups of individuals) who represent strategically important political entities, but whose individual power position is not high.</p>
<p>Examples include student exchanges between the United States and China,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn70"><sup>70</sup></xref> or Japan and China.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn71"><sup>71</sup></xref> China&#x2019;s Confucius Institutes, which target individuals with lower power position, but of countries with which China&#x2019;s bilateral ties are considerable, are similarly placed in this quadrant of salient strategic publics.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn72"><sup>72</sup></xref></p>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_1871191X-13020004_022" sec-type="head2">
<title><bold><italic>Remote Strategic Publics</italic></bold></title>
<p>Remote strategic publics refer to individuals &#x2014; or groups of individuals &#x2014; who represent political entities that are strategically unimportant from the public diplomat&#x2019;s viewpoint, and whose individual power position or status is not high.</p>
<p>One example is William Hague&#x2019;s media-covered campaign travel to Rwanda and the Democratic Republic of Congo to meet with survivors of sexual violence in March 2013.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn73"><sup>73</sup></xref> Another example is the trip, as noted earlier in this article, enjoyed by the Pakistani camel herder Bashir Ahmad to the United States in October 1961 following an <italic>en passant</italic> invitation by <sc>US</sc> President Lyndon Johnson during a visit to Pakistan.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn74"><sup>74</sup></xref></p>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_1871191X-13020004_023" sec-type="head2">
<title><bold><italic>Global Mass Publics</italic></bold></title>
<p>The centre of the two axes in Fig. 1 above can be conceptualized as global mass publics, which &#x2018;merely consists of an aggregation of people who are separate, detached, anonymous&#x2019;,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn75"><sup>75</sup></xref> and affiliated to a vast range of political entities, be they strategically important or not. Global mass publics always co-vibrate as targets in any public diplomacy act, because &#x2014; regardless of the immediately involved strategic public &#x2014; the global audience inevitably has the potential to receive news about anything that is made public. Public diplomats thus always communicate to global mass publics, and most often they do so consciously.</p>
<p>While strategic publics and global mass publics may be distinguishable in many cases, sometimes they may be identical. For example, the proclamation of a new geopolitical doctrine by the <sc>US</sc> president sends a signal that intentionally reaches global mass publics (through mediatized channels).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn76"><sup>76</sup></xref> A posting on Twitter by a powerful public diplomat with high network centrality can also quickly cascade down to global mass publics.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn77"><sup>77</sup></xref></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_1871191X-13020004_024" sec-type="head1">
<title><bold>A Heuristic Device for Multiple Publics</bold></title>
<p>It would be wrong to assume that a case study may identify simply one type of strategic public. The targeted individuals who are immediately, if not physically, located in a public diplomacy setting are usually not the only addressees. Other audiences likewise receive diplomatic signals from the same action.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn78"><sup>78</sup></xref> For example, when Russian President Vladimir Putin wrote an op-ed in <italic>The New York Times</italic> about the Syrian crisis in 2013, he not only used that specific medium as a strategic public whose channel he publicly utilized, perhaps by directly contacting a leading editor, but the op-ed also sought to clarify his policies for the American (if not global) mass publics. Moreover, given the complexity of the geopolitical situation in which so many actors were involved, Putin &#x2018;could mean vastly different things to different players in the crisis, and hence there is no single representation, identity or relationship, but rather a context of polysemy&#x2019; in which he established relational ties, each of which are independently analysable, with a variety of strategic publics.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn79"><sup>79</sup></xref> When the United States invited 29 French personalities to come to the United States in 1985 with a grant from the <sc>IVLP</sc>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn80"><sup>80</sup></xref> this arguably not only changed the relationships between each of the 29 participants and the United States, but it also sent a signal (perhaps of goodwill) to the French government. Or, if <sc>US</sc> President Barack Obama, on his trip to China in November 2009, accepted an interview with the liberal Chinese newspaper <italic>Southern Weekly</italic>, while declining an interview with the stricter party-controlled China Central Television (<sc>CCTV</sc>), then it is not only <italic>Southern Weekly</italic> or its journalist who is involved in this public diplomacy act, but also <sc>CCTV</sc>, the Chinese government, China&#x2019;s mass public and even the domestic <sc>US</sc> mass public.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn81"><sup>81</sup></xref> Each of these communicative signals sent to the numerous players involved may have different effects. The analyst can independently explore the communicative and relational ties established and maintained on each level.</p>
<p>Gary D. Rawnsley distinguished between public diplomacy and media diplomacy by their different audiences and suggested that in public diplomacy, public diplomats use media to target foreign publics, while in media diplomacy, they address foreign officials.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn82"><sup>82</sup></xref> However, as stated earlier in this article, one cannot safely disentangle an immediate strategic public from the mass public, and it would not provide a sound overall analysis if one was to focus merely on one strategic public to the detriment of the others. Public diplomacy is always multidirectional; even if it directly engages only one individual in its immediate setting, the act can simultaneously become known to global mass publics via a mediatized public diplomacy.</p>
<p>A heuristic device that seeks to analyse cases of public diplomacy acts will include at least three levels of the public diplomats&#x2019; targets. First, the traditional government-to-government level; second, the strategic public(s) who are immediately placed into the public diplomacy setting; and, finally, the mass public level. This threefold disaggregation enables analysts to trace the different relational linkages that are established by a public diplomacy act towards the multiple addressees. To illustrate this with Fig. 2, the researcher who analyses a case study should aim to clarify the relational mechanisms that are graphically represented by the black arrows. The most intensive relational act is likely to be pursued with the immediate strategic public, whereas the relational element that links the public diplomat to the mass publics is likely to consist of a mere signal communicated in a mediated one-way flow.</p>
<fig id="f2-303272">
<label><sc>FIGURE 2</sc></label>
<caption>
<title><italic>A three-level model of public diplomacy</italic> (<italic>with arrows to denote relational ties to be explored</italic>)</title>
</caption>
<graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="1871191X_013_03_s002_i0002.jpg" alt-version="yes"/>
</fig>
<p>It is possible that the traditional diplomatic level equals the strategic public &#x2014; such as when the South Korean President conferred a state award upon the Indonesian head of state, as noted above. It is also possible that the global mass publics equal strategic publics &#x2014; as may be the case with governmental Twitter accounts or with the declaration of geopolitical doctrines. It is nevertheless helpful to distinguish them conceptually, lest one overlooks the signals and ties that the public diplomat sends to multiple recipients or sustains with them.</p>
<p>The proposed three-level model serves as a basis, but can be developed further by disaggregating the traditional intergovernmental level and the mass public level into various components (see Fig. 3). Tamir Sheafer and Itay Gabay did so by distinguishing between British mass publics and <sc>US</sc> mass publics in their case study of Israel&#x2019;s and the Palestinian Authority&#x2019;s contest over international agenda- and frame-building.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn83"><sup>83</sup></xref> In his analysis of a Polish initiative that sought a revival of Polish Jewish culture, Thomas Just focused on governmental engagements with domestic constituencies;<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn84"><sup>84</sup></xref> and Kingsley Edney, in his account of Chinese soft power, cites that Chinese public diplomacy programmes are directed towards both foreign and domestic mass publics, but each with a distinct emphasis.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn85"><sup>85</sup></xref></p>
<fig id="f3-303272">
<label><sc>FIGURE 3</sc></label>
<caption>
<title><italic>An analytical model for public diplomacy in which the traditional intergovernmental level and the mass public level are disaggregated into various components</italic></title>
</caption>
<graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="1871191X_013_03_s002_i0003.jpg" alt-version="yes"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="B10.1163_1871191X-13020004_025" sec-type="head1">
<title><bold>Discussion and Conclusion</bold></title>
<p>This article sought to elucidate and organize conceptual types of strategic publics based on dimensions inspired by social psychology and diplomatic theories centring on representation. These dimensions significantly broaden the continua of strategic publics, so that it includes actors about whose role public diplomats and scholars have hitherto been uncertain or even blind: official governmental publics; domestic constituencies; and weaker or remote populations. Moreover, it provided a three-level heuristic device that can be utilized by case studies in order not to overlook public diplomacy&#x2019;s implications among multiple actors. Both the typology and the tool to analyse multiple publics are not ends in themselves, but serve as stimulators of further research to conceptualize strategic publics more clearly.</p>
<p>The question that the article sought to answer was not quite Paul Sharp&#x2019;s &#x2018;in relations between human collectives, who is to be represented, why and how?&#x2019;,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn86"><sup>86</sup></xref> but a descriptive &#x2018;who <italic>can</italic> be represented?&#x2019;, based on underlying theoretical assumptions of diplomatic representation. However, the &#x2018;why and how?&#x2019; remain unanswered, although one may at least posit that the strategies are always contingent on the public diplomats&#x2019; understanding of their targets, and on foreign policy&#x2019;s &#x2018;national interest&#x2019;, which always &#x2018;varies with time and circumstance&#x2019;.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn87"><sup>87</sup></xref> These are precisely the aspects that empirical research can explore.</p>
<p>Future studies should find &#x2018;distinct and predictable patterns&#x2019;<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn88"><sup>88</sup></xref> associated with each sub-set of strategic publics, and offer guidance to formulate hypotheses as to what distinguishes each type in terms of underlying strategies and relational effects.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn89"><sup>89</sup></xref> Intuitive assumptions may suppose, for instance, that imminent strategic publics are addressed when public diplomats seek short-term goals; that the engagement of protocollary strategic publics may decline over time; that a vigorous integration of salient strategic publics indicates a conscious use of &#x2018;soft power&#x2019; considerations in foreign policy priorities; and that remote strategic publics may be neglected, but their inclusion could lead to more sympathetic responses among mass publics. In light of the polysemy of audiences, one may also posit that one-way signals to mass publics are hardly effective in the short term, whereas the directly involved immediate strategic publics experience intense relational consequences during and after their participation in the public diplomacy act.</p>
<p>The typology and the three-level heuristic device introduced in this article may serve as the beginning of an &#x2018;effort to give conceptual meaning&#x2019;<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn90"><sup>90</sup></xref> to the distinct types of strategic publics. Thorough empirical research can enhance our understandings of strategic publics and their relationships to public diplomats, but also the grounds on which the targets are chosen, and the consequences of each type of choice.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<bio>
<p><bold>Andreas Pacher</bold> <italic>studied International Relations at Sciences Po in Paris, France, and at Fudan University in Shanghai, China, as well as law at the University of Vienna, Austria. He has written various journalistic articles on state awards, state-sponsored prizes, public diplomacy and East European politics for Austrian and French magazines. He worked as a jurist in Vienna, is a secretary at the</italic> Internationale Kulturwissenschaftliche Gesellschaft Wien <italic>and Editor-in-Chief of</italic> Nouvelle Europe.</p>
</bio>
<fn-group>
<fn id="fn1"><p>1 Kathy R. Fitzpatrick, &#x2018;Defining Strategic Publics in a Networked World: Public Diplomacy&#x2019;s Challenge at Home and Abroad&#x2019;, <italic>The Hague Journal of Diplomacy</italic>, vol. 7, no. 4 (2012), pp. 421&#x2013;440, at p. 424.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn2"><p>2 This definition is based on, and follows the considerations of, Kirk Hallahan, &#x2018;Inactive Publics: The Forgotten Publics in Public Relations&#x2019;, <italic>Public Relations Review</italic>, vol. 26, no. 4 (2000), pp. 499&#x2013;515, at pp. 501&#x2013;502.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn3"><p>3 Colin Elman, &#x2018;Typologies in Qualitative Studies of International Politics&#x2019;, <italic>International Organization</italic>, vol. 59, no. 2 (2005), pp. 293&#x2013;326, at p. 295.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn4"><p>4 David Collier, Jody LaPorte and Jason Seawright, &#x2018;Putting Typologies to Work: Concept Formation, Measurement, and Analytic Rigor&#x2019;, <italic>Political Research Quarterly</italic>, vol. 65, no. 1 (2012), pp. 217&#x2013;232; Kevin B. Smith, &#x2018;Typologies, Taxonomies, and the Benefits of Policy Classification&#x2019;, <italic>Policy Studies Journal</italic>, vol. 30, no. 3 (2002), pp. 379&#x2013;395.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn5"><p>5 Sasson Sofer, &#x2018;The Diplomat as a Stranger&#x2019;, <italic>Diplomacy &#x0026; Statecraft</italic>, vol. 8, no. 3 (1997), pp. 179&#x2013;186, at p. 180.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn6"><p>6 Alisher Faizullaev, &#x2018;Diplomacy and Self&#x2019;, <italic>Diplomacy &#x0026; Statecraft</italic>, vol. 17, no. 3 (2006), pp. 497&#x2013;522, at p. 501.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn7"><p>7 Paul Sharp, &#x2018;For Diplomacy: Representation and the Study of International Relations&#x2019;, <italic>International Studies Review</italic>, vol. 1, no. 1 (1999), pp. 33&#x2013;57.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn8"><p>8 James Der Derian, &#x2018;Mediating Estrangement: A Theory for Diplomacy&#x2019;, in James Der Derian, <italic>Critical Practices of International Theory: Selected Essays</italic> (London and New York: Routledge, 2009), pp. 7&#x2013;31.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn9"><p>9 James Pamment, &#x2018;The Mediatization of Diplomacy&#x2019;, <italic>The Hague Journal of Diplomacy</italic>, vol. 9, no. 3 (2014), pp. 253&#x2013;280, at p. 255.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn10"><p>10 Charles A.W. Manning, <italic>The Nature of International Society</italic> (London: G. Bell and Sons, 1962), p. 42.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn11"><p>11 Faizullaev, &#x2018;Diplomacy and Self&#x2019;, p. 517.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn12"><p>12 Jacquie L&#x2019;Etang, &#x2018;Public Relations and Diplomacy in a Globalized World: An Issue of Public Communication&#x2019;, <italic>American Behavioral Scientist</italic>, vol. 53, no. 4 (2009), pp. 607&#x2013;626, at p. 616.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn13"><p>13 James Der Derian, <italic>On Diplomacy. A Genealogy of Western Estrangement</italic> (Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1987), p. 109.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn14"><p>14 Sofer, &#x2018;The Diplomat as a Stranger&#x2019;, p. 184.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn15"><p>15 Ellen Huijgh, &#x2018;Changing Tunes for Public Diplomacy: Exploring the Domestic Dimension&#x2019;, <italic>Exchange: The Journal of Public Diplomacy</italic>, vol. 2, no. 1 (2011), pp. 62&#x2013;73; Kathy R. Fitzpatrick, <italic>US Public Diplomacy&#x2019;s Neglected Domestic Mandate: CPD Perspectives on Public Diplomacy</italic> (Los Angeles, <sc>CA</sc>: Figueroa Press, 2010); and Fitzpatrick, &#x2018;Defining Strategic Publics in a Networked World&#x2019;, pp. 437&#x2013;440.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn16"><p>16 Bruce Gregory, &#x2018;Mapping Boundaries in Diplomacy&#x2019;s Public Dimension&#x2019;, <italic>The Hague Journal of Diplomacy</italic>, vol. 11, no. 1 (2016), pp. 11&#x2013;25, at pp. 6&#x2013;8.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn17"><p>17 Giles Scott-Smith, &#x2018;Introduction: Private Diplomacy, Making the Citizen Visible&#x2019;, <italic>New Global Studies</italic>, vol. 8, no. 1 (2014), pp. 1&#x2013;7, at p. 3.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn18"><p>18 Paul Sharp, &#x2018;Diplomats, Diplomacy, Diplomatic Studies, and the Future of International Relations and International Studies&#x2019;, <italic>International Studies Review</italic>, vol. 13 (2011), pp. 716&#x2013;719, at p. 718.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn19"><p>19 Nigel M. de Bussy and Lorissa Kelly, &#x2018;Stakeholders, Politics and Power: Towards an Understanding of Stakeholder Identification and Salience in Government&#x2019;, <italic>Journal of Communication Management</italic>, vol. 14, no. 4 (2010), pp. 289&#x2013;305, at p. 290.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn20"><p>20 James E. Grunig and Fred C. Repper, &#x2018;Strategic Management, Publics, and Issues&#x2019;, in James E. Grunig (ed.), <italic>Excellence in Public Relations and Communication Management</italic> (Hillsdale, <sc>NJ</sc>: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates), pp. 117&#x2013;157, at p. 129.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn21"><p>21 Jeong-Nam Kim, Lan Ni and Bey-Ling Sha, &#x2018;Breaking Down the Stakeholder Environment: Explicating Approaches to the Segmentation of Publics for Public Relations Research&#x2019;, <italic>Journalism and Mass Communication Quarterly</italic>, vol. 85, no. 4 (winter 2008), pp. 751&#x2013;768, at p. 761.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn22"><p>22 Susan T. Fiske, Amy J.C. Cuddy and Peter Glick, &#x2018;Universal Dimensions of Social Cognition: Warmth and Competence&#x2019;, <italic>Trends in Cognitive Sciences</italic>, vol. 11, no. 2 (2007), pp. 77&#x2013;83, at p. 77.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn23"><p>23 Fiske <italic>et al</italic>., &#x2018;Universal Dimensions of Social Cognition&#x2019;, at p. 77.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn24"><p>24 R. Edward Freeman, <italic>Strategic Management: A Stakeholder Approach</italic> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2010), p. 25.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn25"><p>25 Ronald K. Mitchell, Bradley R. Agle and Donna J. Wood, &#x2018;Toward a Theory of Stakeholder Identification and Salience: Defining the Principle of Who and What Really Counts&#x2019;, <italic>The Academy of Management Review</italic>, vol. 22, no. 4 (1997), pp. 853&#x2013;886.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn26"><p>26 Vanessa Magness, &#x2018;Who are the Stakeholders Now? An Empirical Examination of the Mitchell, Agle, and Wood Theory of Stakeholder Salience&#x2019;, <italic>Journal of Business Ethics</italic>, vol. 83, no. 2 (2008), pp. 177&#x2013;192, at p. 179.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn27"><p>27 James E. Grunig, &#x2018;A Situational Theory of Publics: Conceptual History, Recent Challenges and New Research&#x2019;, in Danny Moss, Toby MacManus and Dejan Ver&#x010D;i&#x010D; (eds), <italic>Public Relations Research: An International Perspective</italic> (London: Thomson, 1997), pp. 3&#x2013;46.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn28"><p>28 Kim <italic>et al</italic>., &#x2018;Breaking Down the Stakeholder Environment&#x2019;, p. 752.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn29"><p>29 Hallahan, &#x2018;Inactive Publics&#x2019;.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn30"><p>30 Alison van Rooy, &#x2018;A New Diplomacy? How Ambassadors (Should) Deal with Civil Society Organizations&#x2019;, in R. Wolfe (ed.), <italic>Diplomatic Missions: The Ambassador in Canadian Foreign Policy</italic> (Kingston, <sc>ON</sc>: Queen&#x2019;s University, 1997); see also Brian Hocking, Jan Melissen, Shaun Riordan and Paul Sharp, <italic>Futures for Diplomacy: Integrative Diplomacy in the 21st Century</italic> (The Hague: Netherlands Institute of International Relations &#x2018;Clingendael&#x2019;, 2012), pp. 43&#x2013;48.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn31"><p>31 Hans Tuch, <italic>Communicating with the World: US Public Diplomacy Overseas</italic> (New York: St. Martin&#x2019;s Press, 1990), p. 3.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn32"><p>32 Jarol B. Manheim, <italic>Strategic Public Diplomacy and American Foreign Policy: The Evolution of Influence</italic> (New York: Oxford University Press, 1994), p. 4.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn33"><p>33 Sharp, &#x2018;For Diplomacy&#x2019;.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn34"><p>34 Geoffrey Cowan and Amelia Arsenault, &#x2018;Moving from Monologue to Dialogue to Collaboration: The Three Layers of Public Diplomacy&#x2019;, <italic>Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science</italic>, vol. 616 (2008), pp. 10&#x2013;30, at p. 17.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn35"><p>35 Jarim Kim, &#x2018;Public Relations and Public Diplomacy in Cultural and Educational Exchange Programs: A Coorientational Approach to the Humphrey Program&#x2019;, <italic>Public Relations Review</italic>, vol. 42 (2016), pp. 135&#x2013;145, at p. 136.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn36"><p>36 Sofer, &#x2018;The Diplomat as a Stranger&#x2019;, p. 180.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn37"><p>37 Joseph S. Nye, <italic>Soft Power: The Means to Success in World Politics</italic> (New York: Perseus Books, 2004), p. 16.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn38"><p>38 James Pamment, &#x2018;What Became of the New Public Diplomacy? Recent Developments in British, US and Swedish Public Diplomacy Policy and Evaluation Methods&#x2019;, <italic>The Hague Journal of Diplomacy</italic>, vol. 7, no. 3 (2012), pp. 313&#x2013;336, at p. 319.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn39"><p>39 Pamment, &#x2018;What Became of the New Public Diplomacy?&#x2019;, p. 325.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn40"><p>40 Pamment, &#x2018;What Became of the New Public Diplomacy?&#x2019;, pp. 329&#x2013;330.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn41"><p>41 Pamment, &#x2018;What Became of the New Public Diplomacy?&#x2019;, p. 314.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn42"><p>42 Xiong Chengyu, &#x2018;Coexist, Complement, Converge and Innovate: Public Diplomacy of US&#x2013;China Internet Industry Forum&#x2019;, <italic>Telematics and Informatics</italic>, vol. 30 (2013), pp. 331&#x2013;334.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn43"><p>43 Giles Scott-Smith, &#x2018;Mutual Interests? US Public Diplomacy in the 1980s and Nicolas Sarkozy&#x2019;s First Trip to the United States&#x2019;, <italic>Journal of Transatlantic Studies</italic>, vol. 9, no. 4 (2011), pp. 326&#x2013;341, at p. 332.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn44"><p>44 Andrew F. Cooper, <italic>Celebrity Diplomacy</italic> (London: Routledge, 2007).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn45"><p>45 Donald Lien and Chang Hoon Oh, &#x2018;Determinants of the Confucius Institute Establishment&#x2019;, <italic>The Quarterly Review of Economics and Finance</italic>, vol. 54 (2014), pp. 437&#x2013;441.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn46"><p>46 Andreas Pacher, &#x2018;Being Friends with Transnistria: Emotional Politics via State Awards&#x2019;, <italic>Nouvelle Europe</italic> (18 February 2017), available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="url" xlink:href="http://www.nouvelle-europe.eu/en/being-friends-transnistria-emotional-politics-state-awards">http://www.nouvelle-europe.eu/en/being-friends-transnistria-emotional-politics-state-awards</ext-link>.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn47"><p>47 Giles Scott-Smith, &#x2018;Mapping the Undefinable: Some Thoughts on the Relevance of Exchange Programs within International Relations Theory&#x2019;, <italic>The Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science</italic>, vol. 616 (2008), pp. 173&#x2013;195, at p. 175.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn48"><p>48 William A. Hachten and James F. Scotton, <italic>The World News Prism: Global Media in an Era of Terrorism</italic> (Ames, <sc>IA</sc>: Iowa State University Press, 6th edition 2002), p. 104.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn49"><p>49 Robert M. Entman, &#x2018;Theorizing Mediated Public Diplomacy: The US Case&#x2019;, <italic>Press/Politics</italic>, vol. 13, no. 2 (2008), pp. 87&#x2013;102, at p. 89.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn50"><p>50 Cowan and Arsenault, &#x2018;Moving from Monologue to Dialogue to Collaboration&#x2019;, pp. 16&#x2013;17.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn51"><p>51 Karl E. Weick, &#x2018;Theory Construction as Disciplined Imagination&#x2019;, <italic>The Academy of Management Review</italic>, vol. 14, no. 4 (1989), pp. 516&#x2013;531; and Thomas J. Chermack, &#x2018;Disciplined Imagination: Building Scenarios and Building Theories&#x2019;, <italic>Futures</italic>, vol. 39 (2007), pp. 1&#x2013;15.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn52"><p>52 Jim Murphy, &#x2018;Engagement&#x2019;, in <italic>Engagement: Public Diplomacy in a Globalized World</italic> (London: Foreign &#x0026; Commonwealth Office, 2008), p. 11, as cited in Fitzpatrick, &#x2018;Defining Strategic Publics in a Networked World&#x2019;, p. 440.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn53"><p>53 Weick, &#x2018;Theory Construction as Disciplined Imagination&#x2019;, p. 523.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn54"><p>54 Jian Wang, &#x2018;Managing National Reputation and International Relations in the Global Era: Public Diplomacy Revisited&#x2019;, <italic>Public Relations Review</italic>, vol. 32 (2006), pp. 91&#x2013;96, at p. 94.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn55"><p>55 Paul Sharp, &#x2018;Who Needs Diplomats? The Problems of Diplomatic Representation&#x2019;, <italic>International Journal</italic>, vol. 52, no. 4 (1997), pp. 609&#x2013;634, at p. 630.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn56"><p>56 Bruce Gregory, &#x2018;Mapping Boundaries in Diplomacy&#x2019;s Public Dimension&#x2019;, <italic>The Hague Journal of Diplomacy</italic>, vol. 11, no. 1 (2016), pp. 1&#x2013;25.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn57"><p>57 Fiske <italic>et al.</italic>, &#x2018;Universal Dimensions of Social Cognition&#x2019;, p. 77.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn58"><p>58 Gregory, &#x2018;Mapping Boundaries in Diplomacy&#x2019;s Public Dimension&#x2019;, p. 10.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn59"><p>59 See Kim <italic>et al</italic>., &#x2018;Breaking Down the Stakeholder Environment&#x2019;, p. 753.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn60"><p>60 Cowan and Arsenault, &#x2018;Moving from Monologue to Dialogue to Collaboration&#x2019;.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn61"><p>61 Elizabeth Dubois and Devin Gaffney, &#x2018;The Multiple Facets of Influence: Identifying Political Influentials and Opinion Leaders on Twitter&#x2019;, <italic>American Behavioral Scientist</italic>, vol. 58, no. 10 (2014), pp. 1260&#x2013;1277.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn62"><p>62 Fitzpatrick, &#x2018;Defining Strategic Publics in a Networked World&#x2019;; and Dubois and Gaffney, &#x2018;The Multiple Facets of Influence&#x2019;.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn63"><p>63 Jian Wang and Tsan-Kuo Chang, &#x2018;Strategic Public Diplomacy and Local Press: How a High-Profile &#x201C;Head-of-State&#x201D; Visit was Covered in America&#x2019;s Heartland&#x2019;, <italic>Public Relations Review</italic>, vol. 30 (2004), pp. 11&#x2013;24.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn64"><p>64 &#x2018;<italic>Bag dae-tong-lyeong, yu-do-yo-no jeon in-do-ne-si-a dae-tong-lyeong seo-hun</italic>&#x2019; [President Park with the Former Indonesian President Yudhoyono], <italic>Naver</italic> (19 November 2014), available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="url" xlink:href="http://news.naver.com/main/read.nhn?mode=LSD&#x0026;mid=sec&#x0026;sid1=100&#x0026;oid=001&#x0026;aid=0007255568">http://news.naver.com/main/read.nhn?mode=LSD&#x0026;mid=sec&#x0026;sid1=100&#x0026;oid=001&#x0026;aid=0007255568</ext-link>.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn65"><p>65 Xiong, &#x2018;Coexist, Complement, Converge and Innovate&#x2019;.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn66"><p>66 Scott-Smith, &#x2018;Mutual Interests?&#x2019;.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn67"><p>67 David Filipov, &#x2018;What is the Russian Order of Friendship, and Why Does Rex Tillerson Have One?&#x2019;, <italic>Washington Post</italic> (13 December 2016).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn68"><p>68 James Pamment, &#x2018;Digital Diplomacy as Transmedia Engagement: Aligning Theories of Participatory Culture with International Advocacy Campaigns&#x2019;, <italic>New Media &#x0026; Society</italic> (2015), pp. 1&#x2013;17.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn69"><p>69 See also Alan K. Henrikson, &#x2018;Sovereignty, Diplomacy, and Democracy: The Changing Character of &#x201C;International&#x201D; Representation &#x2014; from State to Self?&#x2019;, <italic>The Fletcher Forum of World Affairs</italic>, vol. 37, no. 3 (2013), pp. 111&#x2013;140, at p. 112.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn70"><p>70 Emily T. Metzgar, &#x2018;Institutions of Higher Education as Public Diplomacy Tools: China-Based University Programs for the 21st Century&#x2019;, <italic>Journal of Studies in International Education</italic> (2015), pp. 1&#x2013;19.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn71"><p>71 Donglin Han and David Zweig, &#x2018;Images of the World: Studying Abroad and Chinese Attitudes towards International Affairs&#x2019;, <italic>The China Quarterly</italic>, no. 202 (2010), pp. 290&#x2013;306.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn72"><p>72 Lien and Oh, &#x2018;Determinants of the Confucius Institute Establishment&#x2019;.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn73"><p>73 Pamment, &#x2018;Digital Diplomacy as Transmedia Engagement&#x2019;, p. 8.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn74"><p>74 Cowan and Arsenault, &#x2018;Moving from Monologue to Dialogue to Collaboration&#x2019;, pp. 16&#x2013;17.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn75"><p>75 Herbert Blumer, &#x2018;The Mass, the Public, and Public Opinion&#x2019;, in Bernard Berelson (ed.), <italic>Reader in Public Opinion and Communication</italic> (New York: Free Press, 2nd edition 1966), at pp. 186&#x2013;187.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn76"><p>76 James Pamment, &#x2018;Strategic Narratives in US Public Diplomacy: A Critical Geopolitics&#x2019;, <italic>Popular Communication</italic>, vol. 12 (2014), pp. 48&#x2013;64.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn77"><p>77 Entman, &#x2018;Theorizing Mediated Public Diplomacy&#x2019;; Dubois and Gaffney, &#x2018;The Multiple Facets of Influence&#x2019;.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn78"><p>78 For the role of signals in diplomacy, see Christer J&#x00F6;nsson and Martin Hall, &#x2018;Communication: An Essential Aspect of Diplomacy&#x2019;, <italic>International Studies Perspectives</italic>, vol. 4 (2003), pp. 195&#x2013;210.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn79"><p>79 Pamment, &#x2018;The Mediatization of Diplomacy&#x2019;, p. 259.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn80"><p>80 Scott-Smith, &#x2018;Mutual Interests?&#x2019;.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn81"><p>81 Sharon LaFraniere and Jonathan Ansfield, &#x2018;In Obama Interview, Signs of China&#x2019;s Heavy Hand&#x2019;, <italic>The New York Times</italic> (19 November 2009).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn82"><p>82 Gary D. Rawnsley, <italic>Media Diplomacy: Monitored Broadcasting and Foreign Policy</italic> (Leicester: Centre for the Study of Diplomacy, University of Leicester, 1995).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn83"><p>83 Tamir Sheafer and Itay Gabay, &#x2018;Mediated Public Diplomacy: A Strategic Contest Over International Agenda Building and Frame Building&#x2019;, <italic>Political Communication</italic>, vol. 26 (2009), pp. 447&#x2013;467.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn84"><p>84 Thomas Just, &#x2018;Public Diplomacy and Domestic Engagement: The Jewish Revival in Poland&#x2019;, <italic>Place Branding and Public Diplomacy</italic>, vol. 11, no. 4 (2015), pp. 263&#x2013;275.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn85"><p>85 Kingsley Edney, &#x2018;Soft Power and the Chinese Propaganda System&#x2019;, <italic>Journal of Contemporary China</italic>, vol. 21, no. 78 (2012), pp. 899&#x2013;914, at pp. 905&#x2013;907.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn86"><p>86 Sharp, &#x2018;Diplomats, Diplomacy, Diplomatic Studies, and the Future of International Relations and International Studies&#x2019;, p. 718.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn87"><p>87 George F. Kennan, &#x2018;Diplomacy Without Diplomats?&#x2019;, <italic>Foreign Affairs</italic> (September/October 1997).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn88"><p>88 Smith, &#x2018;Typologies, Taxonomies, and the Benefits of Policy Classification&#x2019;, p. 379.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn89"><p>89 Collier <italic>et al</italic>., &#x2018;Putting Typologies to Work&#x2019;; and Smith, &#x2018;Typologies, Taxonomies, and the Benefits of Policy Classification&#x2019;.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn90"><p>90 Collier <italic>et al</italic>., &#x2018;Putting Typologies to Work&#x2019;, p. 220.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
</back>
</article>